[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Who among these is an ancient linguist of India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Patanjali",
            "b) Tista Bagchi",
            "c) Noam Chomsky",
            "d) Kshetresa Chandra Chattopadhyaya"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Linguistics is the study of language. Patanjali, the ancient linguist of India, considered it as a human expression uttered out by speech organs. The other three are modern linguists belonging to 19th and 20th century. "
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which of these people perceives language as a means to interpret human experience?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anthropologist",
            "b) Sociologist",
            "c) Philosopher",
            "d) Students of literature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Language means different things to different people. To an anthropologist, it is a form of cultural behaviour whereas to a sociologist, it is a means of communication between members of a social group. Students of literature may consider it as an artistic medium, while those of philosophy may consider it a means to interpret human experience. "
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which of these words is based on the phenomena, ‘Onomatopoeia’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cuckoo",
            "b) Book",
            "c) Door",
            "d) Blackboard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Language is a social phenomenon.  Man may not have needed a language if he had not made himself a part of a social group. A language must thus convey social realities if it is to become an effective means of communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of linguistics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Historical",
            "b) Personal",
            "c) Comparative",
            "d) Synchronic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Language is arbitrary, that is there is no logical link between any gjven feature of a language and its meaning. The only exception is in the case of onomatopoeia, where the words imitate the sounds of their referents. Here, cuckoo is the sound made by the bird which is how the bird got its name."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which of these finds out how a certain set of people use a language at a given time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diachronic Linguistics",
            "b) Comparative Linguistics",
            "c) Synchronic Linguistics",
            "d) Historical Linguistics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Linguistics is a scientific study of language. It can be divided into three types namely: Historical or Diachronic Linguistics, Synchronic Linguistics and Comparative Linguistics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a level of language?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phonology",
            "b) Grammar",
            "c) Running",
            "d) Semantics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Synchronic Linguistics finds out how a certain set of people use a language at a given time. Historical or Diachronic Linguistics studies the link between language and history. Comparative Linguistics studies the comparison between two or more languages. "
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Which of these terms refers to the study of speech sounds of a given language and their function within the sound system of that language?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phonetics",
            "b) Phonology",
            "c) Syntax",
            "d) Morphology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: R.H. Robins recommends three levels of structure of language.  These are phonology, grammar and semantics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of these is the study of meaning of words, and the development of the meaning of words?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morphemics",
            "b) Phonetics",
            "c) Semantics",
            "d) Syntax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phonology refers to the study of speech sounds of a given language and their function within the sound system. Phonetics is the study of speech process. Syntax and Morphology are sub-levels of the grammatical system."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of these terms refer to the study of speech process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phonology",
            "b) Phonetic substances",
            "c) Phonetics",
            "d) Semantics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phonetics is the study of speech processes. It includes the anatomy, neurology and pathology of speech. It also includes the articulation, classification and perception of speech sounds. It shouldn’t be confused with Phonology, which is the study of speech sounds of a given language and their function within the sound system of that language; or Semantics, which is a field of Linguistics that is primarily concerned with meaning in various languages. "
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of phonetics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Articulatory",
            "b) Personal",
            "c) Acoustic",
            "d) Auditory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phonetics can be divided into three main branches. These are Articulatory phonetics, Accoustic phonetics and Auditory phonetics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which of these terms refer to the study of hearing and perception of speech sounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Articulatory phonetics",
            "b) Acoustic phonetics",
            "c) Auditory phonetics",
            "d) Laboratory phonetics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Articulatory phonetics is the study of the movement of the speech organs while words are being uttered. Acoustic phonetics is the study of physical properties of speech sounds which include frequency and amplitude. "
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "What is the term used for ingressive air-sounds produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Claps",
            "b) Snap",
            "c) Clicks",
            "d) Beats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Auditory phonetics is the study of hearing and perception of speech sounds. Articulatory phonetics deals with the movement of speech organs whereas Acoustic phonetics deals with the physical properties of speech sounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Which of these refer to the sound features of a language?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morphemics",
            "b) Phonetic substances",
            "c) Phonetics",
            "d) Syntax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Laboratory phonetics is experimental phonetics which uses instruments  ( both mechanical and electronics) to study sounds. "
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "What does the phonetic symbol d represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voiced bilabial plosive",
            "b) Voiceless palatal plosive",
            "c) Voiced alveolor plosive",
            "d) Voiced dental fricative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Normally, speech sounds are produced on egressive pulmonic air-stream during exhilaration. In few cases, ingressive air sounds are also made. Such speech sounds are called clicks."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "What is the full form of IPA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indian Phonetic Alphabet",
            "b) International Phonetic Alphabet",
            "c) International Phonetic Agreement",
            "d) Indian Phonetic Agreement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phonetic substances refer to the sound features of a language, as studied by articulatory, acoustic and auditory phonetics. It is different from Phonetics, which studies the kinds of sounds made by human speech using the speech organs; and also different from Morphemics, which is the synchronic study of words. "
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "What does the sign /  /  represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phonetic transcription",
            "b) Centralization",
            "c) Voiced bilabial nasal",
            "d) Rising- falling pitch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The symbol d refers to Voiced alveolor plosive. The symbol b refers to Voiced bilabial plosive and c refers to Voiceless palatal plosive."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "What is a consonant called when it is placed at the end of a syllable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Releasing consonant",
            "b) Arresting consonant",
            "c) Dental consonant",
            "d) Alveolar consonant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A syllable is a unit of pronunciation which consists only a vowel or a vowel and a consonant. The nucleus of the syllable is the vowel; the consonant is its marginal element."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is the structure in the following syllable : pack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CVC",
            "b) CV",
            "c) VCC",
            "d) VC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a consonant is placed at the end of a syllable, it is called an arresting consonant. When it is placed at the beginning of a syllable, it is called a releasing consonant. "
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "f and z are examples of :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bilabial consonant",
            "b) Sibilant consonant",
            "c) Dental consonant",
            "d) Alveolar consonant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In CVC, C stands for consonant and V stands for vowel. For the word pack, the first letter p is a consonant. The last two letters c and k are also consonants, but they come together to make a single sound. Between these two consonants, there’s the vowel a. Hence the structure of the word would be CVC."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a voiceless sound component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) b",
            "b) d",
            "c) c",
            "d) g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A consonant is a letter of the alphabet which represents a sound that can only be articulated with a vowel. Sibilant consonant like f and z are exceptions which can be pronounced without the help of a vowel."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "According to the place of articulation, which of these is not a type of consonant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bilabial",
            "b) Dental",
            "c) Velar",
            "d) Public"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The voiced sounds in English are l,b,d,g,v,z,m,n,r,w,j, that is, the vocal cords must be used in order to produce the sound made by these letters. All vocoids and semi-vowels are voiced sounds. The letter c’s sound on the other hand, can be made without using one’s voice. Hence, c is a voiceless sound component."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which of these consonants are the one whose place of articulation is the lower lip and upper teeth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bilabial",
            "b) Dental",
            "c) Labio-dental",
            "d) Glottal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to the place of articulation, consonants are classified into 9 types. These are Bilabial, Dental, Labio-dental, Alveolar, Post-alveolar, Palato-alveolar, Palatal, Velar and Glottal."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "According to the placement of the tongue, which of these is not a type of vowel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross vowels",
            "b) Front vowels",
            "c) Back vowels",
            "d) Central vowels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the labio-dental consonant, the place of articulation is the lower lip and the upper teeth whereas for the bilabial consonant, it is the upper and lower ljp. For the dental consonant, it is the teeth and tip of the tounge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which of the following vowels is an example of back vowel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) i",
            "b) e:",
            "c) u",
            "d) a"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The classification of vowels can be made into three depending on the placement of the tongue. These are front vowels, back vowels and central vowels."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an article?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An",
            "b) A",
            "c) This",
            "d) The"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A, an and the are called articles in English grammar. An is used before a vowel or silent h. The word ‘this’ can be a pronoun (Eg: This is my seat.); or a determiner (Eg: This cake is the tastiest one.)"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What are a, an and the collectively called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indefinite articles",
            "b) Demonstrative adjectives",
            "c) Definite articles",
            "d) Demonstrative adverbs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A is used before a consonant or a vowel sounding like a consonant. For example, A man, a unit, a useful thing, a one rupee- note. "
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which if these belong to indefinite articles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) A and an",
            "c) An and the",
            "d) A and the"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A, an and the are adjectives. They are called demonstrative adjectives.  A and an are indefinite articles and the is called a definite article."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of these belong to definite articles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A and the",
            "b) The",
            "c) A and an",
            "d) An and the"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Articles are classified into two types.  They are indefinite and definite articles. Indefinite articles are a and an. Definite article includes only the. The correct statement is : A child must respect his parents."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank : Bismillah Khan plays  _____ shehnai with great skill.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a",
            "b) an",
            "c) the",
            "d) a or the"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A and an are called the indefinite articles because they leave indefinite the person or thing spoken of. Thus, a boy means any boy. The is a definite article."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank : Neha has left for ___ United States of America.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a",
            "b) the",
            "c) an",
            "d) to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The is called a definite article because it speaks of some particular person or thing. Example : He is the boy who teased me. A and an are indefinite articles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "In which of these cases, the article is not omitted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before names of materials",
            "b) Before names of relations",
            "c) Before the names of certain books",
            "d) Before languages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Articles are usually omitted before proper nouns. For example, Shakespeare had a comprehensive soul. An article used before a proper noun makes it a common noun. "
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Her brother is an engineer.",
            "b) Her brother is a engineer.",
            "c) Her brother is the engineer.",
            "d) Her brother is engineer."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Before the names of certain books, the definite article the is used. For example, The Mahabharat . Before languages, names of materials and relations, articles are omitted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank : He is ___ honest lawyer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a",
            "b) an",
            "c) the",
            "d) very"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: little is used chiefly with better or more in formal english. For example, His second composition was little (= not much) better than his first. "
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Little as an adverb can’t be used with which one of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verbs",
            "b) Unfavourable adjectives",
            "c) Countable nouns",
            "d) Comparative adverbs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When we define or classify someone or something we use a/an + singular count noun. In the above question, the noun starts with a vowel, so we use an. "
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Find the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sun rises in the east.",
            "b) The sun rises in the east.",
            "c) Sun rises in east.",
            "d) The sun rises in east."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When we mention someone or something for the first time, we use a/ an not the. When we mention the same person or thing again, we use the. For example: I saw a dog on the street today. The dog looked hungry."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Fill in the blanks : ___ more you concentrate, ___ better you become.",
        "Options": [
            "a) the, a",
            "b) the, the",
            "c) a, a",
            "d) the, then"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is : Family is a unit of society. We use a or an as per the sound of the vowel and not the actual vowel. Here the vowel u is pronounced as yoo."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "A preposition is placed before which of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noun",
            "b) Verb",
            "c) Adjective",
            "d) Noun or pronoun"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A preposition is a word placed before a noun or a pronoun to show in what relation the person or thing denoted by it stands in regard to something else. For example: There is a dog in the garden. For this sentence, the preposition is in, and it is placed before the noun garden. Another example is: The boy’s cellphone lay beside him. In this sentence, the preposition is beside, and it precedes the pronoun him."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "In which of these cases, the preposition is always placed at the end?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Relative pronoun",
            "b) Reciprocal pronoun",
            "c) Possessive pronoun",
            "d) Reflexive pronoun"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The noun or pronoun which is used with a preposition is called its object. It is in the accusative case and is said to be governed by the preposition. Example: There is a dog in the garden. The noun ‘garden’ is in the accusative case governed by the preposition ‘in’."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a simple preposition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) From",
            "b) Through",
            "c) Above",
            "d) With"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The preposition is always placed at the end when the object is an interrogative or a relative pronoun. For example:  Here is the money that you asked for. , What are you thinking of."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank:  He acted ________ my instructions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) agreeable to",
            "b) according to",
            "c) in favour of",
            "d) in course of"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At, by, for, from, in, of, off, as, out, through, till, to, up, with are simple prepositions. Compound prepositions are generally formed by prefixing a preposition to a noun, adjective or an adverb. Example, above."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which of these is a participial?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Underneath",
            "b) Beside",
            "c) Considering",
            "d) Along with"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phrase prepositions are group of words used with the force of single preposition. Examples are in addition to, in place of, in spite of, etc.. For example: Call me in case of an emergency."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: We walked ___ the river and back.",
        "Options": [
            "a) till",
            "b) to",
            "c) at",
            "d) about"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Here we use a phrase preposition, according to. The correct statement will be: He acted according to my instructions."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Fill in with appropriate preposition : I have not seen the television ______ yesterday.",
        "Options": [
            "a) from",
            "b) since",
            "c) till",
            "d) for"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Participials are present participles of verbs which are used absolutely without any noun or pronoun being attached to them. For all practical purposes, they have become prepositions. In the above question, the word Considering is the present continuous tense of the word consider, and it’s used as a participial preposition. Example: Considering his age, the Sports Council felt that he was too old to be in the international team.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of these relations is not indicated by prepositions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Place",
            "b) Age",
            "c) Time",
            "d) Manner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prepositions normally indicate nine relations. These are place, time, agency, manner, cause, possession, measure, contrast, inference."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which of the options draws a relation between the preposition and manner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fought among themselves",
            "b) Came before time",
            "c) Cut it with a knife",
            "d) Fought with courage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phrase in which the preposition is related with manner is: Fought with courage, as it describes the manner with which the action was done. In the phrase: Fought among themselves, the preposition is related with place; in the phrase: Came before time, it is related to time; and in the phrase: Cut with a knife, the preposition is related with a possession, that is the knife."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: He lives ___ Bezonbagh ___ Nagpur.",
        "Options": [
            "a) in, at",
            "b) at, in",
            "c) at, on",
            "d) on, at"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false as it is related to cause and not to possession. An example of a phrase where the preposition is related to possession is ‘The girl with red dress’."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Fill in: The cat sprang ___ me.",
        "Options": [
            "a) on",
            "b) upon",
            "c) in",
            "d) at"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In is used with name of countries and large towns. However, at is used for small towns and villages. So the statement will be, He lives at Bezonbagh in Nagpur."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) She walked till the end of the road.",
            "b) She walked to the end of the road.",
            "c) She walked at the end of the road.",
            "d) She walked on the end of the road."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is: The cat sprang upon me. The preposition on is often used when speaking of things which are at rest, and upon is used for things in motion. Example of on: the cat sat on the mat. In is used when speaking of location (He is in China.), or manner (He was in great pain). At is used for location (No one is at home right now.), or for time (The appointment is at 10 o’clock.)"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: The factory began production _____ 22nd July.",
        "Options": [
            "a) since",
            "b) from",
            "c) by",
            "d) at"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: She walked to the end of the road. Till is used for time and to is used for place. For example: She slept till the sun was overhead."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kunal has been absent for five days.",
            "b) Kunal has been absent since five days.",
            "c) Kunal has been absent from five days.",
            "d) Kunal has been absent till five days."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From is used before a noun or phrase denoting some point of time, but, is used with the non-perfect tenses. Hence, the statement will be: The factory began production from 22nd July. "
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which of these nouns takes the preposition for after it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alliance",
            "b) Ambition",
            "c) Bargain",
            "d) Experience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The noun ‘ambition’ takes the preposition for after it. Alliance and bargain take the preposition with after them and experience takes the preposition of after it."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which of these adjectives takes the preposition with after it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accused",
            "b) Absorbed",
            "c) Drenched",
            "d) Anxious"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Some nouns take the preposition from after them. For example, descent, digression, escape, exemption, inference. "
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of these verbs takes the preposition for after it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beware",
            "b) Mourn",
            "c) Delight",
            "d) Determine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The adjective drenched takes the preposition with after it. The adjective accused takes of after it, absorbed takes in and anxious takes for after it."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a preposition of time and date?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At",
            "b) On",
            "c) In",
            "d) With"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The verb mourn takes the preposition for after it. The verb beware takes the preposition of, delight takes the preposition in and determine takes the preposition on after it."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: Aahna didn’t reach her class ____ noon.",
        "Options": [
            "a) by",
            "b) to",
            "c) till",
            "d) at"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: At, on, by, before, in are prepositions of time and date. For example; at dusk, on Sunday, by 10 p.m. on Monday. With is a preposition used to indicate possession, or feeling. Examples: He cut the vegetables with a knife; He looked at me with sympathy."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The hooligans broke in the factory.",
            "b) The hooligans broke into the factory.",
            "c) The hooligans broke onto the factory.",
            "d) The hooligans broke at the factory."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Prepositions from, since, for, during also denote time. From mostly precedes to/till/until. For example, This shop is open from 10 a.m. to 8 p.m."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: The boy ___ brown hair stole my book.",
        "Options": [
            "a) in",
            "b) with",
            "c) from",
            "d) below"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To is used for time and place; till/until is used only for time. We use till/until and not to when there is no from. The correct statement is: Aahna didn’t reach her class till noon."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of tense?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present",
            "b) Language",
            "c) Past",
            "d) Future"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A tense shows the time of action and its degree of completeness. It is broadly classified into three types: present, past and future tense."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of present tense?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple",
            "b) Continuous",
            "c) Imperfect",
            "d) Perfect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A particular tense can further be divided into four types. They are: simple, continuous, perfect, perfect continuous. "
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which of these statements belongs to perfect continuous tense?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I was loving",
            "b) I had written",
            "c) I had been writing",
            "d) I shall be writing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The perfect form (in present, past or future)  denotes an action which has been completed, and is in a perfect state. For example: I have loved, I had loved, I shall have loved."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "The statement I have written a letter belongs to which of these tenses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple present tense",
            "b) Present perfect tense",
            "c) Present continuous  tense",
            "d) Present perfect continuous tense"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The perfect continuous tense combines the meanings of the both the perfect and continuous tense. For example: I have been writing, I had been writing, I shall have been writing. I was loving is past continuous tense, I had written is past perfect tense, and I shall be writing is future continuous tense. "
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which of these statements belong to present continuous tense (plural)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) We are writing a letter.",
            "b) She is writing a letter.",
            "c) They were writing a letter.",
            "d) We were writing a letter."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The present perfect tense denotes an action which has been completed, and is in a perfect state in the present form. For example, I have written a letter, I have loved, I have been to Chennai. Simple present tense would be: I write letters. Present continuous tense would be: I am writing a letter. Present perfect continuous tense would be: I have been writing a letter."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Fill in with past perfect tense: I _______ my homework when my uncle arrived.",
        "Options": [
            "a) completed",
            "b) had completed",
            "c) was completing",
            "d) had been completing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: We are writing a letter. In the present continuous form the event denotes an action that is still continuing or is yet not completed. It can be in singular or plural form."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of simple present tense?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I am going to Delhi tomorrow.",
            "b) There she goes!",
            "c) He has just gone out.",
            "d) I am reading the gita."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The past continuous tense is used to denote an action going on at some time in the past. The time of the action may or may not be indicated. For example: We were watching television all day. "
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I am a student for over three years now.",
            "b) I have been a student for over three years now.",
            "c) I am being a student for over three years now.",
            "d) I was a student for over three years now."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The past perfect tense describes an action completed before a certain moment in the past. For example, I had completed homework when my uncle arrived."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to express habitual actions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present perfect tense",
            "b) Simple present tense",
            "c) Past continuous tense",
            "d) Present continuous tense"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The simple present tense is used to express habitual actions. For example: I bathe every morning.  It is also used to express general truths. "
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Choose the correct  statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) He sweared that he had not stolen the bag.",
            "b) He swore that he had not stolen the bag.",
            "c) He was swearing  that he had not stolen the bag.",
            "d) He swears that he had not stolen the bag."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Simple present tense is used to indicate a future event where the context tells us the future time. So the statement belongs to Simple present tense. In vivid narrative, it is also used as substitute for simple past."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "In which of these cases, present continuous tense is not used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For an action going on at the time of speaking.",
            "b) For a temporary action which may not be actually happening at the time of speaking.",
            "c) For an action that is planned to take place in the near future.",
            "d) For an action which began sometime in the past and is still continuing."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: He swore that he had not stolen the bag. The simple past tense of most irregular verbs is not formed with -d or -ed."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: He said that he ______ tomorrow.",
        "Options": [
            "a) will come",
            "b) would come",
            "c) will be coming",
            "d) has been coming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The statement: A letter is being written by me, belongs to the present continuous tense in passive form. In active form, the statement would be: I am writing a letter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "If the subject is of singular number, third person; in what number and person will the verb be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Singular number, first person",
            "b) Singular number, third person",
            "c) Plural number, first person",
            "d) Plural number, third person"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The verb takes the same number as its subject. It must agree with its subject in number and person. If the subject is of singular number, third person, the verb must also be of the singular number, third person. "
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The quality of books were poor.",
            "b) The quality of books was poor.",
            "c) The quality of books are poor.",
            "d) The quality of books were being poor."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true.   If two singular nouns refer to the same person or thing, the verb must be singular. Example: My friend, philosopher and guide is here. If different persons are referred,; My friend, the philosopher and the guide are here."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: Neither he nor I ____ present.",
        "Options": [
            "a) were",
            "b) was",
            "c) are",
            "d) am"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The quality of books was poor. The subject is ‘the quality of books’ and not ‘books’. The phrase ‘quality of books’ is in singular form, so it should not take a plural verb."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The fire caused many damages.",
            "b) The fire caused much damage.",
            "c) The fire caused many damage.",
            "d) The fire caused much damages."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. If singular subjects are preceded by every and each, the verb is singular. For example: Every child and parent brings his own food."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: The ship ___ set sail.",
        "Options": [
            "a) has",
            "b) is",
            "c) was",
            "d) have"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is: Neither he nor I was present. Two or more singular subjects connected by or, nor, either, neither take the verbs in singular."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Fill in the blank: None of the students ___ happy with the teacher.",
        "Options": [
            "a) were",
            "b) was",
            "c) have",
            "d) has"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Your best bet is free tickets. The subject is, ‘your best bet, not ‘free tickets’. Hence it should take a singular verb."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Infinitive is also known as :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verb adjective",
            "b) Verb  noun",
            "c) Verb pronoun",
            "d) Adverb noun"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Verbs can be classified into two types. It is classified into finite and non finite. A verb which is limited by number or person is called a finite verb. For example, They always find fault with me."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Which of these verbs is  accompanied by to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Let",
            "b) Make",
            "c) See",
            "d) Determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A verb which is not limited by person and number is called the infinitive. For example, They always try to find fault with me. "
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is an infinitive called when it is used as a noun?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple infinitive",
            "b) Complex infinitive",
            "c) Present infinitive",
            "d) Qualifying infinitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An infinitive is a kind of noun with certain features of a verb, especially that of taking an object. Thus, infinitive is a verb noun."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": " When infinitive is active, what forms can it be present in?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present",
            "b) Perfect",
            "c) Present and perfect",
            "d) Continuous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The infinitive is usually accompanied by word to though with certain verbs like bid, let, make, see, hear, etc.. we use the infinitive without to. For example: I will pray = I am determined to pray. "
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) It cost the management 10 crores to built the hospital.",
            "b) It cost the management 10 crores to build the hospital.",
            "c) It cost the management 10 crores to building the hospital.",
            "d) It cost the management 10 crores for build the hospital."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The infinitive with or without adjuncets may be used, like a noun. As the subject of the verb, as: To err is human. "
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of these words is not used in the bare infinitive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to",
            "b) that",
            "c) is",
            "d) are"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The infinitive can broadly be classified into two types : Bare infinitive and split infinitive. There are certain verbs and expression where to is not used. These are called the bare infinitive. "
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because he  failed, the school may cancel his admission.",
            "b) Because he had failed, the school may cancel his admission.",
            "c) Because he is failed, the school may cancel his admission.",
            "d) Because he have  failed, the school may cancel his admission."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phrase ‘to be done’ belongs to present infinitive passive.  Example for perfect infinitive passive is  ‘to have been done’ and for perfect infinitive is ‘to have done’."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "After which of these nouns, an infinitive can’t be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure",
            "b) Ambition",
            "c) Desire",
            "d) Escape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Normally, no words are used between to and the verb. The only exception is the split infinitive. The other type is bare infinitive."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "For which of these cases do but/except not take the bare infinitive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) do + anything",
            "b) do + nothing",
            "c) do + everything",
            "d) do + something"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Because he had failed, the school may cancel his admission. When we refer to something that happened or was expected to happen before now, we use a perfect infinitive, not a present infinitive. "
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "In which of these cases, the continuous infinitive is not used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) After auxiliary verbs",
            "b) With certain verbs like appear, happen, seem.",
            "c) After hope and promise.",
            "d) At the beginning of a sentence."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The infinitive can also be used after certain nouns. These nouns include ability, ambition, demand, desire, effort, failure, promise, refusal, scheme, wish."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of these forms represent the perfect infinitive continuous?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to + have + past participle",
            "b) to + have been + present participle",
            "c) to be + present participle",
            "d) to + present participle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The infinitive can also be used with too/enough after  certain adjective and adverbs. For example: The spoon was too hot to touch. "
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "What is a participle called when it is used as a simple qualifying adjective in front of a noun?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Past participle",
            "b) Participial adjective",
            "c) Participial noun",
            "d) Participial adverb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. A participle is a verb which is partly a verb and partly an adjective. It is that form of a verb which has the characteristics of a verb as well as an adjective. For example, Hearing the noise, the old man got up with a start. "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of present participle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Studying",
            "b) Having finished",
            "c) Stolen money",
            "d) Having been told"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a participle called when it is used as a simple qualifying adjective in front of a noun, it is called a participial adjective. Foe example, A rolling stone gathers no moss. "
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Being in haste, the door was left open.",
            "b) Being in haste, he left the door open.",
            "c) Being in haste, door was open.",
            "d) Door was left open being in haste."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The present participle ends with -ing. It represents an action which is going on or is incomplete or imperfect. So the statement is, I met  boy carrying a box of chocolates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "What is a participle linked to the wrong noun or pronoun called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Misrelated participle",
            "b) Wrong participle",
            "c) Incorrect  participle",
            "d) Misleading  participle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here, the participle is ‘knowing’. In certain cases, accepted usage permits the following constructions where the participle is left without a proper subject or reference. Such a participle is called the impersonal absolute."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement :",
        "Options": [
            "a) The school usually remains opened till 5 pm.",
            "b) The school usually remains open till 5 pm.",
            "c) The school usually remain open till 5 pm.",
            "d) The school usually remains opens till 5 pm."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is : Blinded by hate, he lashed out with a knife. A past participle represents a completed action or state of the thing mentioned. The above statement is an example. "
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "What is the part of the sentence which denotes the person or thing about which something is said?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Predicate",
            "b) Subject",
            "c) Phrase",
            "d) Clause"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A clause is a group of words which forms part of a sentence, and contains a subject and a predicate of its own. "
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple",
            "b) Continuous",
            "c) Compound",
            "d) Complex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The part of the sentence which denotes the person or thing about which something is said, is called the subject of the sentence. For example, Mili sings a song. Here, Mili is the subject. "
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "What is a sentence with one principal clause and one or more subordinate clauses called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compound sentence",
            "b) Complex sentence",
            "c) Simple sentence",
            "d) Principal sentence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the sentence, the group of words ‘when evening came’ make some sense, but it doesn’t make complete sense. It however, has a subject (evening) and predicate  (came when) of its own. Such a group of words is called a clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of subordinate clause?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adverb",
            "b) Verb",
            "c) Adjective",
            "d) Noun"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phrase in the sentence is ‘at sunset ‘. The group of words ‘at sunset ‘ makes some sense but does not make complete sense. Such a group of words is called a phrase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I’ll write a letter when I will reach Mumbai.",
            "b) I’ll write a letter when I reach Mumbai.",
            "c) I’ll write a letter as I reach Mumbai.",
            "d) I’ll write a letter when I shall reach Mumbai."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sentences can be broadly classified into three types. They are : Simple sentences, Compound sentences and Complex sentences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of degree of comparison?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive",
            "b) Negative",
            "c) Comparative",
            "d) Superlative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The  statement is false. Adjectives that change in form to show comparison are called degree of comparison. Example, pretty : prettier: prettiest. "
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "What is the superlative of little?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less",
            "b) Lesser",
            "c) Least",
            "d) Worst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Degrees of comparison can be classified into three types. They are : positive degree, comparative degree and superlative degree. For example , good is positive, better is comparative and best is superlative."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "What is the positive of inner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In",
            "b) Inmost",
            "c) Innermost",
            "d) most in"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is an irregular comparison of adjective. The comparative of little is less or lesser and the superlative of little is least. The superlative of bad is worst."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Which of the following words’ comparative degree is formed by simply adding the word more before the adjective itself?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Nice",
            "c) Heavy",
            "d) Difficult"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is : Platinum is more precious than any metal. When two objects are compared with each other, the latter terms of comparison must exclude the former. "
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Milk is more cheap than water.",
            "b) Milk is cheaper than water.",
            "c) Milk is cheap than water.",
            "d) Milk is cheapest than water."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The positive of inner is in. The superlative of inner is innermost. The word inmost does not exist; and the phrase most in is grammatically incorrect. This is an irregular comparison of adjectives. "
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) She is one of the most prettiest girl in the class.",
            "b) She is the prettiest girl in the class.",
            "c) She is the most prettiest girl in the class.",
            "d) She is one of the pretty girl in the class."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the initial, positive form of an adjective has two or more syllables, the comparative degree is formed by adding the adverb more with the positive. The superlative degree is formed by adding the adverb most before the positive. In the case, positive: difficult, comparative: more difficult, superlative: most difficult. Smaller adjectives with less syllables can be converted to comparative and superlative forms by adding the suffixes ‘er’ and ‘est’ respectively. Eg: small, smaller, smallest. "
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is the positive of most (quantity)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) many",
            "b) much",
            "c) more",
            "d) good"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true.  When the positive ends in y, preceded by a consonant, the y is changed into i before adding er and est. For example: heavy, heavier and heaviest."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "What is the comparative of far (physical distance)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Farther",
            "b) Further",
            "c) Farthest",
            "d) More far"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The comparative in er is not used when we compare two qualities in the same person or thing. For example: Meera is more pretty ( not prettier) than wise. The suffix ‘er’ is used only when comparing two completely different entities or a specific quality in two different entities. Example: Ann is prettier than Mary. "
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "What is the superlative of late (with respect to time)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Later",
            "b) Latter",
            "c) Latest",
            "d) Last"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The positive of most (quantity) is much and its comparative is more. The positive of most (number) is many."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I’m not as intelligence as he.",
            "b) I’m not as intelligence as him.",
            "c) I’m not intelligent than he.",
            "d) I’m not intelligent than him."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The comparative of far is farther and its superlative is farthest. More far is incorrect and should not be used. Also, farther should not be confused with further. The two words cannot be used interchangeably. The word farther is used to denote physical distance between two locations. For example: According to the map, we have to walk farther. The word further is used in a more metaphorical sense. For example: This topic needs to be discussed further."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kalidas is the greatest of all other poets.",
            "b) Kalidas is the greatest of all poets.",
            "c) Kalidas is the greater of all other poets.",
            "d) Kalidas is the greater of all poets."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The comparative of late with respect to time is later and superlative is latest. With respect to position, the comparative is latter and the superlative is last."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) He is unhappy than his friend.",
            "b) He is more unhappy than his friend.",
            "c) He is unhappier than his friend.",
            "d) He is most unhappy than his friend."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Karan is older than Kashish. Elder is not used followed by than and so we use older. "
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of these does not come under transformation of sentences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changing active voice into passive voice.",
            "b) Changing passive voice into active voice.",
            "c) Changing affirmative sentences into negative sentences.",
            "d) Changing interrogative sentences into assertive sentences and their reverse."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transformation of sentences have various forms. These include : Changing active voice into passive voice, changing affirmative sentences into negative sentences, changing interrogative sentences into assertive sentences and their reverse, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Assertive",
            "b) Interrogative",
            "c) Complicated",
            "d) Imperative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are four kinds of sentences. They are : Assertive sentence, interrogative sentence, imperative sentence and exclamatory sentence."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of assertive sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Affirmative",
            "b) Informal",
            "c) Negative",
            "d) Emphatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. An assertive sentence states a fact, describes a thing or reports an event. For example, He wrote a letter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Assertive sentence can also be called as :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emphatic sentence",
            "b) Declarative sentence",
            "c) Imperative sentence",
            "d) Exclamatory sentence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An assertive sentence can be classified into three types. They are : Affirmative sentence, negative sentence and emphatic sentence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which of these words is not used to transform non-emphatic sentence to emphatic sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Do",
            "b) Does",
            "c) Did",
            "d) Has"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An assertive sentence states a fact, describes a thing or reports an event. Assertive sentence can also be called as declarative sentence or a statement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of affirmative sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can you do this?",
            "b) What a pretty girl!",
            "c) Everyone accepts his version.",
            "d) Please open the door."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The  statement is false. An imperative sentence expresses some command, request, advice, etc. For example: Sit down, please. "
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which of these is an assertive sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Why waste time in reading trash?",
            "b) I wish that I were healthy again.",
            "c) How beautiful is the rainbow!",
            "d) Please have a look at the brochure."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sentence ‘ I wish that I were healthy again.’ is an assertive sentence. An assertive sentence states a fact, describes a thing or reports an event. It is also called a declarative sentence or a statement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of these conjunctions is not used in the transformation of simple into compound sentences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alternative conjunctions",
            "b) Illative conjunctions",
            "c) Cumulative conjunctions",
            "d) Complex conjunctions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Neha is not as pretty as Mili. Both of them are assertive sentences but one is affirmative and the other is negative. "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "A verb in a simple sentence CANNOT be expanded to which of the following clauses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noun clause",
            "b) Verb clause",
            "c) Adjective clause",
            "d) Adverb clause"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A simple sentence can be converted to a complex sentence by expanding a verb or phrase into a subordinate clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which of these conjunctions is not used during the conversion of compound to complex sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cumulative conjunctions",
            "b) Alternative conjunctions",
            "c) Illative conjunctions",
            "d) Principal conjunctions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three types of subordinate clauses to which a verb or phrase can be expanded. They are noun clause, adjective clause and adverb clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Verbs of which of these do not form their passive with the passive infinitive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liking",
            "b) Loving",
            "c) Wanting",
            "d) Advice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The passive of an active tense is formed by inserting the verb ‘to be’ into the same tense as the active verb and adding the past participle of the active verb. For example, active voice: He threw the ball. Passive voice: The ball was thrown by him."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Verbs of which of these form their passive by using the passive form of the main verb.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wanting",
            "b) Wishing",
            "c) Liking",
            "d) Command"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is : The book is being written by him. The passive of continuous tenses requires the present continuous form of “to be”. And the verb ‘writing’ needs to be converted to its past participle form, that is, ‘written’."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an use of the passive voice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When we know about the doer of the action.",
            "b) When the subject of the active verb would be people.",
            "c) To avoid awkward or ungrammatical sentences.",
            "d) When an active form would create problems for the speaker."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Auxiliary + infinitive combinations are made passive by using a passive infinitive. Example : Active : You must write this letter. Passive : This letter must be written by you."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noun",
            "b) Verb",
            "c) Preposition",
            "d) Object"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Verbs of liking/ loving/ wanting/ wishing etc + object + infinitive form their passive with the passive infinitive. "
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Indirect speech is also called as :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reported speech",
            "b) Quoted speech",
            "c) Simple speech",
            "d) Principal speech"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Direct speech is when one quotes the exact words spoken by a speaker. For example, Neha said “I am very tired now.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of these prepositions is used with inquire or demand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Is",
            "b) At",
            "c) Of",
            "d) On"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. If the reported speech expresses some universal truth, habit, historical incident or permanent fact, its tense does not change even when the reporting verb is in the past tense. For example, direct speech: The teacher said, “New Delhi is the capital on India.” Reported speech: The teacher said that New Delhi is the capital of India."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of these forms are used to report negative commands?",
        "Options": [
            "a) not + infinitive",
            "b) no + infinitive",
            "c) command + infinitive",
            "d) object + infinitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: He said, “Alas ! I am undone.” An exclamatory sentence must have an exclamatory mark."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of these verbs don’t follow the object + infinitive form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beg",
            "b) Order",
            "c) Invite",
            "d) Pray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. While changing a question into indirect speech, the reporting verb must be changed into ask, inquire or demand. Also, the question mark must be removed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an adjectival?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noun",
            "b) Verb",
            "c) Adverb",
            "d) Gerund"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nouns are modified by nouns, participles, gerunds, adverbs, possessives and prepositional phrases. They are called adjective equivalents or adjectivals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of a participle as a modifier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A canvas trouser",
            "b) Running nose",
            "c) A walking stick",
            "d) A student’s pen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ‘Running nose’ is an example of a participle as a modifier. ‘A canvas trouser’ is an example of a noun as a modifier. ‘A walking stick’ is an example of a gerund as a modifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which of these is not modified by adverb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verb",
            "b) Adjective",
            "c) Noun",
            "d) Adverb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adjective modify nouns. Adjectives are used in two ways: attributively and predicatively. For example: This is a new car. (attributive use), This car is new. (predicative use)."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an adverb of frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Often",
            "b) Never",
            "c) Usually",
            "d) Smoothly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Suffixes “er” and “est” are added to monosyllabic adjectives to express contrasts. These create comparative and superlative forms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of these sentences is an example of an end position adverb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He normally wakes up at 6 A.M.",
            "b) This car runs smoothly.",
            "c) How wonderful she looks !",
            "d) Why did he visit the zoo?"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adverbs modify verbs, adjectives and adverbs. They are used in different positions. Interrogative adverbs “how”, “when”, “where” and “why” are used in the front position. "
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The principal placed the notice for all students on the notice board.",
            "b) The principal placed on the notice board the notice for all students.",
            "c) The principal placed the notice on the notice board for all students.",
            "d) The principal on the notice board placed the notice for all students."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adverbs like “often”, “never”, “sometimes”, “usually” etc., are placed with verbs. They are adverbs of frequency and are known as mid position verbs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) On opening the window, Neha’s eyes at once fell on the bird.",
            "b) As Neha opened the window, her eyes at once fell on the bird.",
            "c) On opening the window, at once Neha’s eyes fell on the bird.",
            "d) As Neha opened the window, her eyes fell on the bird at once."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: This car runs smoothly. Some adverbs are placed after the verb, and after object when used in the sentence. Due to this reason, they are known as end position adverbs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Coordinating clauses are clauses of ______ rank.",
        "Options": [
            "a) equal",
            "b) unequal",
            "c) different",
            "d) varied"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A conjunction is a word which merely joins together sentences and words. They are also known as sentence connectives. "
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a coordinating conjunction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cumulative",
            "b) Adversative",
            "c) Possessive",
            "d) Alternative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conjunctions can broadly be classified into two types. They are: Co-ordinating conjunctions and subordinating conjunctions. Coordinating clauses are clauses of equal rank."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of subordinating conjunction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Result",
            "b) Time",
            "c) Cause",
            "d) Age"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Co-ordinating conjunctions can be classified into four types. They are: Cumulative, adversative, alternative and illative. "
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Which of these words is not an example of subordinating conjunction related to time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before",
            "b) Till",
            "c) Because",
            "d) Since"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Subordinating conjunctions can be classified into seven types.  They are: time, cause, purpose, result, condition, concession and comparison. "
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) He wants to win. But he doesn’t have the skills to do so.",
            "b) He wants to win, but he doesn’t have the skills to do so.",
            "c) He wants to win and he doesn’t have the skills to do so.",
            "d) He wants to win as he doesn’t have the skills to do so."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Subordinating conjunctions which are related to time are indicated by words like before, till, since. For example, “She reached here after he had left.” ‘Because’ is a conjunction related to reasoning. It joins two clauses wherein one clauses states something and the other clauses provides reason to support the first clause."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Either the action was just or unjust.",
            "b) The action was either just or unjust.",
            "c) The action was just or unjust.",
            "d) The action was just or the action was unjust."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: He wants to win, but he doesn’t have the skills to do so. We don’t place the coordinating conjunctions and, or and but at the beginning of the sentence."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) These men are poor hence they are weak.",
            "b) These men are poor and so they are weak.",
            "c) These men are poor because they are weak.",
            "d) These men are poor since they are weak."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The action was either just or unjust. In correlative conjunctions, each member of the pair should be placed before the same part of the speech. "
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of adversative co-ordinating conjunction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He didn’t raise his hand and he didn’t raise his voice.",
            "b) She was pretty, but she was dumb.",
            "c) Hurry up, else you will lose.",
            "d) You must have not studied hard, for the paper was easy."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: She was pretty, but she was dumb. The adversative co-ordinating conjunction represents contrast. "
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an example of subordinating conjunction related to cause?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because",
            "b) Since",
            "c) As",
            "d) Unless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cause is indicated by words like because, since and as. For example: He didn’t win the race, because he was injured."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which of these words is not used to join the dependent clause with the main clause?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Who",
            "b) When",
            "c) For",
            "d) But"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The clauses may be joined by such connectors as and, but, that, when etc. For example, The water is cold and tasty. "
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which of these words are not used by independent clauses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nor",
            "b) Still",
            "c) And",
            "d) For"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dependent clause can be joined with the main clause by using words like who, when and for. But is used to join independent clauses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "In relative clauses, which of these is used to refer to things?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Who",
            "b) Which",
            "c) That",
            "d) Whom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Independent clauses use the words and, but, or, nor, still and however. For example, “He wanted to go in the car, but it was unserviceable. For is used by dependent clauses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Although he was hurt, but he continued to walk.",
            "b) Although he was hurt, he continued to walk.",
            "c) He was hurt, he continued to walk.",
            "d) Although he continued to walk, he was hurt."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A dependent clause may refer to a noun or pronoun in the main clause. It is joined with the main clause by connectors like what, which, whose, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) There were between 8 to 10 policemen present.",
            "b) There were between 8 and 10 policemen present.",
            "c) There were among 8 to 10 policemen present.",
            "d) There were atleast  8 and 10 policemen present."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In relative clauses, we use which to refer to things, not to people. For example: The student who sits next to me in class comes from China. In this sentence, which isn’t used because people are being referred to. A sentence that uses which to refer to things is: The ice cream flavor which I like, was out of stock at the store."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The gerund is also called as :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verb",
            "b) Noun",
            "c) Verb – noun",
            "d) Adverb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. gerund is a form of verb which ends in -ing, and has the force of a noun or a verb. For example, “Eating is his pet hobby.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "In which of these, the gerund is the subject of the verb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sleeping is his favourite pastime.",
            "b) I love sleeping.",
            "c) I like eating apples.",
            "d) He loves accumulating wealth."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In “Eating is his pet hobby.”, the word “eating” is used as the subject of a verb. Hence it does a work of a noun, and is called a verb-noun. So, the gerund is also called a verb-noun. "
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "In which of these sentences, the gerund is the object of the verb?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I love eating apples.",
            "b) Cleaning is his favourite pastime.",
            "c) Eating is his hobby.",
            "d) Ram was tired of walking."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Sleeping is his favourite pastime. A gerund, like a noun, can be the subject of the verb, but like a verb, it also takes an object. "
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The gerund is the same as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adverb",
            "b) Pronoun",
            "c) Adjective",
            "d) Infinitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: I love eating apples. A gerund, like a noun, can be the object of the verb, but like a verb, it also takes an object. "
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to form a compound gerund form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Past participle",
            "b) Present  participle",
            "c) Perfect  participle",
            "d) Participial adjective"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A gerund, like a noun, can be governed by a preposition, but like a verb, it also takes an object. For example, “He loves accumulating wealth.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "The present participle is also called as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adverb- noun",
            "b) Verbal noun",
            "c) Verbal adjective",
            "d) Verbal pronoun"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gerund and the infinitive are alike. They are both used as nouns, and yet retain the power that a verb has of governing the noun or pronoun in the objective case. "
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "A gerund can not be used as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subject of a noun",
            "b) Object of the transitive verb",
            "c) Object of a preposition",
            "d) Absolutely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compound gerund forms are formed by placing a past participle after the gerunds of “have” and “be”. For example, We are tired after having walked so much. "
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) We must prevent him playing.",
            "b) We must prevent his playing.",
            "c) We must prevent him for playing.",
            "d) We must prevent his from playing."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gerund has the force of a noun and a verb, it is a verbal noun. The present participle has the force of an adjective and a verb, it is called a verbal adjective."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a punctuation mark?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full stop",
            "b) Comma",
            "c) Colon",
            "d) Hashtag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main punctuation marks are full stop, comma, colon, semicolon, question mark, exclamation mark, hyphen, dash, brackets, apostrophe. Hashtag isn’t a punctuation mark. It is a symbol used in social networks, and it has no relevance in English Grammar."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which of these is used after a nominative absolute?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colon",
            "b) Comma",
            "c) Full stop",
            "d) Question mark"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The full stop is used at the end of an indirect question. It is used to mark the close of a complete sentence. Example: I was wondering if you’d be interested in going to the cinema tonight. "
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to separate short co-ordinate clauses of a compound sentence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semicolon",
            "b) Comma",
            "c) Full stop",
            "d) Colon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The comma used before or after a word used to address a person. For example, “Come here, Mohan.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to separate a series of loosely related clauses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comma",
            "b) Full stop",
            "c) Semicolon",
            "d) Colon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The comma is used after a nominative absolute. For example, “ Once over, she returned home in complete peace.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Which of these is used between sentences which are grammatically independent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colon",
            "b) Semicolon",
            "c) Comma",
            "d) Hyphen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The comma is used to separate short co-ordinate clauses of a compound sentence. For example, “ She came, she stooped, she conquered.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to convey proportions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semicolon",
            "b) Colon",
            "c) Comma",
            "d) Hyphen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The semicolon is used to separate a series of loosely related clauses. For example: Today we love what tomorrow we hate; today we seek what tomorrow we shun."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) My aunt who lives in Mumbai is a doctor.",
            "b) My aunt, who lives in Mumbai, is a doctor.",
            "c) My aunt, who lives in Mumbai is a doctor.",
            "d) My aunt who lives in Mumbai, is a doctor."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The colon is used between sentences which are grammatically independent but closely connected in sense. For example, “Truth is the greatest inspiration of all: nothing is of greater value.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I met a beautiful , European woman.",
            "b) I met a beautiful European woman.",
            "c) I met a beautiful European, woman.",
            "d) I met a beautiful , European, woman."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The colon is used to convey certain conventional constructions as to convey proportions like 4 : 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to indicate the omission of a word?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colon",
            "b) Semicolon",
            "c) Comma",
            "d) Apostrophe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The comma is used to indicate the omission of a word, especially a verb; as, “Her first album sold only 2000 copies but her second 2,000,000” "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Which of these is used before co-ordinative conjunctions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comma",
            "b) Full stop",
            "c) Colon",
            "d) Dash"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The comma is used before certain co-ordinative conjunctions; as “To think thus is not intellectual, but stupidity.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to explain a preceding statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comma",
            "b) Hyphen",
            "c) Semicolon",
            "d) Colon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The comma is used before and after a participial phrase. For example, “Alexander, having conquered India, wished to return home.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to indicate the end of a question tag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full stop",
            "b) Question mark",
            "c) Exclamatory mark",
            "d) Colon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The colon is used to explain a preceding statement; as “ A teacher has to perform a role: he must impart information.“ "
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to convey a sudden change or abrupt end of a thought?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comma",
            "b) Colon",
            "c) Dash",
            "d) Hyphen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The question mark is used to indicate the end of polite questions and question tags; as, “ He has won, hasn’t he?” "
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of these is used in the case of titles of books?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brackets",
            "b) Capital Letters",
            "c) Apostrophe",
            "d) Parenthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dash is used to convey a sudden change or abrupt end of a thought. For example, “If he had worked hard – but why cry over spilt milk.” A dash shouldn’t be confused with a hyphen. A hyphen is slightly shorter than a dash, and it is used to connect the parts of a compound word. For example: jack-of-all-trades."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The industrial age saw a rise in the use of machinery.",
            "b) The Industrial age saw a rise in the use of machinery.",
            "c) The Industrial Age saw a rise in the use of machinery.",
            "d) The industrial Age saw a rise in the use of machinery."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The hyphen is a shorter line than the dash. It is used to connect parts of a compound or complex work. For example: pro-active, lion-hearted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) God, the supreme creator and the supreme being is our only hope.",
            "b) God, the Supreme Creator and the Supreme Being is our only hope.",
            "c) God, the Supreme creator and the Supreme being is our only hope.",
            "d) God, the supreme Creator and the supreme Being is our only hope."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Capital letters are used in the case of titles of books, reports and articles. The first letter is capitalised. It is also used in the names of days and months. "
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Courage becomes :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Courageous",
            "b) Couragous",
            "c) Courageable",
            "d) Couragable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The ‘e’ which is silent in any word, is dropped if a suffix beginning with a vowel is added to it. For example, “love” becomes “lovable”."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Rot becomes _____ and pen becomes ______.",
        "Options": [
            "a) roted, pened",
            "b) rotting, pened",
            "c) rotting, penned",
            "d) rotted, penned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: “Courage” becomes “Courageous”. The silent e is retained in words ending with “ce” or “ge”. For example, “induce” become “inducive”."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "A monosyllabic word containing two vowel letters ends with:",
        "Options": [
            "a) k",
            "b) c",
            "c) ck",
            "d) kc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rot becomes rotting and pen becomes penned. A monosyllabic word which ends with a consonant preceded by a single vowel letter has its consonant doubled if a suffix beginning with a vowel is added to it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "A word which is monosyllabic and has one vowel must end with:",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm",
            "b) ll",
            "c) p",
            "d) t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Though most monosyllabic words with one vowel end with “k” (sack, rock, sock and so on), there are some exceptions that end with just “c” (sac, zinc, talc)."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "A word which is monosyllabic and has two vowels must end with:",
        "Options": [
            "a) ll",
            "b) l",
            "c) ck",
            "d) c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A monosyllabic word containing two vowel letters ends with “k” and not “ck”. For example, book, creak, etc.. "
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Which of these words is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allign",
            "b) Align",
            "c) Alignn",
            "d) Alline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A word which is monosyllabic and has one vowel must end with ll. For example, fill, ball, etc.. The only exception to this is “pal”. "
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I asked him if he was leaving.",
            "b) I asked him whether he was leaving.",
            "c) I asked him that if he was leaving.",
            "d) I asked him weather he was leaving."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A word which is monosyllabic and has two vowels must end with l. For example, meal, fool, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The boy gave his examination.",
            "b) The boy took his examination.",
            "c) The teacher took his examination.",
            "d) The boy gave away the examination."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct word is “Align”. It is often misspelt. Other such words are antenna, aperture, beginning, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of these words is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bureau",
            "b) Beaurau",
            "c) Bereau",
            "d) Bureu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct word is “Bureau”. It is often misspelt. Other such words are benefitted, calibre, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "When a word ends with “y”, and the letter before “y” is a consonant; for the various other forms of the word, “y” is replaced with:",
        "Options": [
            "a) e",
            "b) i",
            "c) ie",
            "d) eng"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a word ends with “y”, and the letter before “y” is a consonant, then the “y” is replaced with an “i” before all suffixes except “ing”. For example, “supply” becomes “supplier” or “supplying”."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I should make more exercise.",
            "b) I should take more exercise.",
            "c) I should give more exercise.",
            "d) I should have more exercise."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The vowel u must always follow the consonant q. For example: queer, quint, quotient, etc.. "
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I saw a strange dream last night.",
            "b) I got a strange dream last night.",
            "c) I had a strange dream last night.",
            "d) I faced a strange dream last night."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: I should take more exercise. One can take an exercise, not make exercise. "
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is dirty, throw it.",
            "b) It is dirty, throw it away.",
            "c) It is dirty, give it.",
            "d) It is dirty, give it away."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: I had a strange dream last night. We have a dream, we don’t see or get a dream. "
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) He tore the letter in anger.",
            "b) He tore up the letter in anger.",
            "c) He teared the letter in anger.",
            "d) He teared up the letter in anger."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: My watch is five minutes slow. A watch is slow or fast, not behind or in front or not before or after. "
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which of these words is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longevity",
            "b) Longivity",
            "c) Longevety",
            "d) Longeviety"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct word is Longevity. It is often misspelt. Other such words are liquefy, liaison, mystique, propeller, etc.. "
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Please open the light.",
            "b) Please shut the light.",
            "c) Please turn on the light.",
            "d) Please shut down the light."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Please turn on the light. We turn on or off the light. We don’t open or shut the light. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) He comes always late for practice.",
            "b) He always comes late for practice.",
            "c) He comes late always for practice.",
            "d) He comes late for practice always."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: He always comes late for practice. Adverbs of indefinite time like, ever, never, sometimes and the adverbs almost, hardly, nearby are placed before the principal verb. "
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graham Bell discovered the telephone.",
            "b) Graham Bell found the telephone.",
            "c) Graham Bell invented the telephone.",
            "d) Graham Bell did the telephone."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: I could not persuade him to come to the party. To convince is to make a person believe in something that they initially didn’t believe in. To persuade means to get a person to do something. "
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I met him six years before.",
            "b) I met him six years early.",
            "c) I met him six years ago.",
            "d) I met him six years behind."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Graham Bell invented the telephone. To discover means to find that which already existed. To invent means to make that which did not exist. "
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) I am presently working in Mumbai.",
            "b) I am at present working in Mumbai.",
            "c) I am at presently working in Mumbai.",
            "d) I am present working in Mumbai."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The word “ultrasonic” is an adjective whereas the word “ultra sound” is a noun. "
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) This shop has many rich clients.",
            "b) This shop has many rich customers.",
            "c) This shop has many rich people.",
            "d) This shop has many rich trespassers."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: I met him six years ago. We use ago in counting from the time of speaking to a point in the past; we use before in counting from a distance to a nearer point in the past. "
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Which of the following word is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Etiquette",
            "b) Etiquete",
            "c) Ettiquette",
            "d) Ettiquete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct word is “ Etiquette “. It is often misspelt. Other such words are eliminate, deferred, exaggerate, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Which of these words is an adjective?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cutout",
            "b) Output",
            "c) Saccharin",
            "d) Saccharine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The word saccharine is an adjective. The words cutout, output and saccharin are nouns and not adjectives."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The teacher told me to go to my house at once.",
            "b) The teacher told me to go to my home at once.",
            "c) The teacher told me to go to my building at once.",
            "d) The teacher told me to go to my place at once."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The teacher told me to go to my home at once. A house is a building and a home is a particular house in which one is living."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ground was full of men.",
            "b) The ground was full of people.",
            "c) The ground was full of creatures.",
            "d) The ground was full of beings."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The ground was full of people. We use the word people while referring to human beings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) His trouser is torn.",
            "b) His trousers is torn.",
            "c) His trousers are torn.",
            "d) His trouser are torn."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: He called me stupid. Stupid, foolish, etc. are adjectives. They cannot be used with the article after the verb to be. "
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) The teacher complemented the class.",
            "b) The teacher complimented the class.",
            "c) The teacher complamented the class.",
            "d) The teacher compliemented the class."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: His trousers are torn. Some nouns (as people, clothes, wages, scissors) are not used in the singular. "
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) There were continuous interruptions during the match.",
            "b) There were continually interruptions during the match.",
            "c) There were continual interruptions during the match.",
            "d) There were continued interruptions during the match."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The teacher complimented the class. Complement means to compete whereas compliment means to praise."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Write down your ideas about playing cricket on a paper.",
            "b) On a paper, write down your ideas about playing cricket.",
            "c) About playing cricket on a paper, write down your ideas.",
            "d) Write down about playing cricket on a paper, your ideas."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: There were continual interruptions during the match. Continual means recurring often. Continuous means without a break."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of these months does not have an abbreviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) January",
            "b) December",
            "c) May",
            "d) August"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Full stops must be omitted from abbreviations, unless they are to be retained for clarity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation for October?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ocb",
            "b) Oct",
            "c) Octr",
            "d) Ocr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. No space must be added between abbreviations. The abbreviation of World Health Organisation is WHO and not W.H.O."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation for Thursday?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thu",
            "b) Thur",
            "c) Thurs",
            "d) Thus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The abbreviations for January, December and August is Jan, Dec and Aug respectively. May, June and July are not abbreviated."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of these measurements does not have an abbreviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram",
            "b) Metre",
            "c) Litre",
            "d) Mile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The abbreviation for October is Oct. Abbreviations for February is Feb, November is Nov and December is Dec."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation of Hectometre?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hm",
            "b) hcm",
            "c) hmt",
            "d) htm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The abbreviation for Thursday is Thurs and 6 is Tues. The abbreviation for Sunday is Sun, Monday is Mon and Saturday is Sat."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation of Centilitre?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cl",
            "b) ctl",
            "c) dl",
            "d) clt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A word indicating measurement which has less than four letters is not abbreviated but there are exceptions like mile."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "What is the expansion of a/c?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alternating current",
            "b) Account",
            "c) Association",
            "d) Chartered Accountant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The abbreviation of Hectometre is hm. The abbreviation of Dekametre is dkm and Decimetre is dm."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation for Centigrade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cg",
            "b) C",
            "c) cgr",
            "d) ctg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The abbreviation of Centilitre is cl. The abbreviation for Millilitre is m1l and kilolitre is kl. The abbreviation for Decilitre is dl. "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "What is the expansion of AD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anno domini",
            "b) Aide-de-camp",
            "c) Appendix",
            "d) Adverb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The expansion for AD is Anno domini. It is a calendar term that was used in Julian and Gregorian calendars. The abbreviations for Aide-de-camp, Appendix and Adverb are ADC, app and adv respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "What is the abbreviation for Pound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P",
            "b) Po",
            "c) lb",
            "d) llb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The abbreviation for pound is lb. The abbreviation for microgram is mcg and for ounce is oz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What is the expansion for PABX?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Private Automatic Branch Exchange",
            "b) Public Automatic Branch Exchange",
            "c) Private Annual Branch Exchange",
            "d) Public Annual Branch Exchange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The expansion for PABX is Private Automatic Branch Exchange. The expansion for PBX is Private Automatic  Exchange."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of these means “from the beginning”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ad hoc",
            "b) ab intio",
            "c) a priori",
            "d) ad interim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ad intio is a latin phrase which means “from the beginning”. Ad hoc means “made or done for a particular purpose”. "
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which of these is a French phrase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bona fide",
            "b) De facto",
            "c) Deja vu",
            "d) Blitzkrieg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Déjà vu is a French phrase which means “a sense of having experienced the present”. Bona fide is Latin word which means “real”. De facto is a Latin phrase. Blitzkrieg is a German term referring to a certain military tactic."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of these is an abbreviation for Bachelor of Laws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BL",
            "b) BLL",
            "c) LB",
            "d) LLB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The abbreviation for Bachelor of Laws is LLB. The abbreviation for Doctor of Laws is LLD and Low Frequency is LF. "
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of these means “a monument”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulwark",
            "b) Edifice",
            "c) Facade",
            "d) Portal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Edifile (pronounced as ed-uh-fis) means a monument. Bulwark means a strong defensive wall structure. Façade means the exterior face of a building. A portal is a door, or a gateway.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": " Which of these means “a  tool for boring holes in wood”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger",
            "b) Banister",
            "c) Conduit",
            "d) Laminate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The word “Auger” means a tool for boring holes in wood. Banister means a vertical member to support a handrail. A conduit is a passageway for flow of fluids such as water. To laminate is to cover something with a layer of protective material, usually plastic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Which of these is an abbreviation for Please Reply?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PR",
            "b) RSVP",
            "c) RP",
            "d) RSP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The abbreviation for Please Reply is RSVP (Répondez, S‘il Vous Plaît). The abbreviation for signed is sgd."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of these means “to strain”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Baste",
            "b) Colander",
            "c) Sieve",
            "d) Confectionery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The word sieve means to strain. The word baste means to moisten meat in its own juices during cooking. "
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "The use of possessive case should not be confined to which of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Name of living beings",
            "b) Name of personified objects",
            "c) A few stereotyped phrases",
            "d) Nouns of space denoting a quality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A verb must agree with its subject in both number and person."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Possessive case is also known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genitive case",
            "b) Principal case",
            "c) Qualifying case",
            "d) Main case"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The use of possessive case should be confined to: Name of living beings and personified objects, few stereotyped phrases and nouns of space and time denoting an amount. "
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "An article is used before which of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Common noun, plural number",
            "b) Proper noun, singular number",
            "c) Common noun, singular number",
            "d) Proper noun, plural number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The possessive case is also known as genitive case. For example, “A day’s rest, a month’s duration”, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "An ellipsis is a figure of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) syntax",
            "b) quality",
            "c) amount",
            "d) verb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As a general rule, an article is used before a common noun, singular number; as, “Behave like a man”."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "A participle should never be left without ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) proper reason",
            "b) proper agreement",
            "c) proper purpose",
            "d) proper adverb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The subject of a sentence should not be left without a verb. It is incorrect to say, “He who has suffered most in the cause, let him speak.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One must keep one’s words.",
            "b) One must keep one’s word.",
            "c) One must keep ones words.",
            "d) One must keep ones word."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An ellipsis is a figure of syntax in which a word or words are left out but implied. "
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meena has lost a ten rupees note.",
            "b) Meena has lost a ten rupees notes.",
            "c) Meena has lost a ten rupee note.",
            "d) Meena has lost a ten rupee notes."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A participle should never be left without proper agreement. It is incorrect to say, “ Sitting on the gate, a scorpion stung him”. It is correct to say, “ Sitting on the gate, he was stung by a scorpion”. "
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which of these combinations destroy each other?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive + positive",
            "b) Positive + negative",
            "c) Negative + negative",
            "d) Negative + positive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Pronoun governing a Gerund should be put in possessive case. For example, “ Please forgive my being late.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of these should not be used for adverbs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nouns",
            "b) Adjectives",
            "c) Prepositions",
            "d) Verbs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Adverbs must be placed next to the words they modify. For example, “ He had reached almost to the top when the rope broke.” "
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "In which of these ly is not added?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First",
            "b) Second",
            "c) Third",
            "d) Final"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two negatives destroy each other. They must never be used together unless we wish to make an affirmation. For example: I didn’t do nothing. This is incorrect, as it has two negatives. The correct sentence is: I didn’t do anything."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "______ must not be used with a Correlative.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adjective",
            "b) Noun",
            "c) Adverb",
            "d) Pronoun"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adjectives can’t be used for adverbs.  We should say, “ He came more quickly ( not quicker) than I expected.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "_____ should not be used instead of so.",
        "Options": [
            "a) On the contrary",
            "b) That",
            "c) But",
            "d) However"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In an enumeration say first, secondly, thirdly. First, being itself an adverb, does not need the ly that is frequently added."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) He bought two dozen mangoes.",
            "b) He bought two dozens mangoes.",
            "c) He bought two dozen mango.",
            "d) He bought two dozens mango."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An adverb of degree must not be used with a correlative, unless the usage is colloquial. For example, “ He is very weak.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Who was it written by?",
            "b) Who was it written?",
            "c) By whom was it written?",
            "d) By who was it written?"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: That should not be used instead of so as an adverb. For example: I could reach only so (not that) far. "
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Which of these comes immediately after the noun?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adverb phrase",
            "b) Adjective  phrase",
            "c) Verb phrase",
            "d) Pronoun phrase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. On is used in speaking of things at rest, and upon of things in motion. For example: The clock sat on the bedside table. This is an example of an object at rest. Whereas, in the sentence: She stumbled upon a secret passage; movement is clearly being conveyed."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of these statements is false?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The subject should usually follow the verb.",
            "b) The object usually comes after the verb.",
            "c) When there is an indirect object and a direct object, the indirect precedes the direct.",
            "d) When the adjective is used attributively it comes before the noun which it qualifies."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is: The dog sprang upon him. On is used in speaking of things at rest, and upon of things in motion."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Every statement must have a subject and a _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) noun",
            "b) verb",
            "c) predicate",
            "d) phrase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Till is used of time and to is used of place. For example: I slept till 6 o’clock. "
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Do not make friend with selfish people.",
            "b) Do not make friendship with selfish people.",
            "c) Do not make friends with selfish people.",
            "d) Do not make friendly with selfish people."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The adjective phrase comes immediately after the noun. For example: The top of the handle was broken. "
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) She doesn’t know the reason for his disappearance.",
            "b) She doesn’t know the reason of his disappearance.",
            "c) She doesn’t know the reason at his disappearance.",
            "d) She doesn’t know the reason with his disappearance."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The subject should usually precede the verb. For example: The dog bit the boy. The object usually comes after the verb. "
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Some students are ____ at copying.",
        "Options": [
            "a) adapt",
            "b) adept",
            "c) adopt",
            "d) edept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To be complete, every statement must have a subject and a predicate. In other words, once the subject has been mentioned, there is necessity to say something about it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Father _____ me not to go out in the cold.",
        "Options": [
            "a) adviced",
            "b) advised",
            "c) advice",
            "d) advise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Do not make friends with selfish people. The phrase ‘make friends’ is grammatically correct. "
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to refer to something that happened before the moment of speaking.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present infinitive",
            "b) Perfect  infinitive",
            "c) Bare infinitive",
            "d) Continuous  infinitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The present infinitive is the base form of a verb. This is the form that we look up in a dictionary as be, go, build, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "An infinitive clause may begin with a?",
        "Options": [
            "a) present infinitive",
            "b) perfect  infinitive",
            "c) past infinitive",
            "d) bare infinitive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We must use perfect infinitive if we refer to something that happened or was expected to happen before now (before the moment of speaking). "
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) He obtained passing marks.",
            "b) He obtained pass marks.",
            "c) He obtained passed marks.",
            "d) He obtained passing mark."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A modal verb is followed by a bare infinitive ( not a to- infinitive). For example: I felt that I could never go home again. "
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anil talks French well.",
            "b) Anil chats French well.",
            "c) Anil speaks French well.",
            "d) Anil talk French well."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is : I advised her not to drink it.  We put not and never  in front of the to of a to- infinitive."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ship was drowned.",
            "b) The ship drowned.",
            "c) The ship sank.",
            "d) The ship had sank."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An infinitive clause may begin with a bare infinitive or a to- infinitive. The bare infinitive is more common."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is they who has to leave this place.",
            "b) It is they who have to leave this place.",
            "c) It is them who has to leave this place.",
            "d) It is them who have to leave this place."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: He obtained pass marks. Passing is the present participle form of pass which is to be used here."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "The committee members ______ to the proposal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ascented",
            "b) assented",
            "c) accented",
            "d) acsented"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. When we are trying to show what someone or something is like, we use compared with. While differentiating between two things, we use compared to."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Which of these means “bundle of cotton”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bail",
            "b) Bael",
            "c) Bale",
            "d) Beal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. When we draw attention to the similarities or differences between two things, we use compared with. "
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "_____ were breached during the Hitler’s regime.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Canons",
            "b) Canon",
            "c) Cannon",
            "d) Cannons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The committee members assented to the proposal. Assent means approval or agreement."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Teacher cited many examples to prove his point.",
            "b) Teacher sited many examples to prove his point.",
            "c) Teacher citied many examples to prove his point.",
            "d) Teacher citted many examples to prove his point."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bale means “bundle of cotton” whereas bail means the “temporary release of an accused person awaiting trial”. Bael is a type of Indian fruit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Personal assistant is a ______ of minister.",
        "Options": [
            "a) confidence",
            "b) confident",
            "c) confidential",
            "d) confidant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Canons were breached during the Hitler’s regime. Canon means a general law, rule, principle, or criterion by which something is judged. Cannon is a kind of weapon."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) My friend has several dependents.",
            "b) My friend has several dependants.",
            "c) My friend has several dependaents.",
            "d) My friend has several depandents."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Teacher cited many examples to prove his point. Cite means refer to (a passage, book, or author) as evidence for or justification of an argument or statement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) John and Mark fought a duel.",
            "b) John and Mark fought a dual.",
            "c) John and Mark fought a duet.",
            "d) John and Mark fought a daul."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Personal assistant is a confidant of minister. Confidant means a person with whom one shares a secret or private matter."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Ambassadors have _____ manners.",
        "Options": [
            "a) urban",
            "b) urbane",
            "c) urben",
            "d) urbaen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: My friend has several dependants. Dependant means a person who relies on another, especially a family member, for financial support."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an eponym?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bloomers",
            "b) Boolean",
            "c) Boycott",
            "d) Basket"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Eponym is a word derived from the name of a person. It is a name of a person after whom a discovery, invention, place etc. is named. "
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Cassegrain Telescope is named after?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A German astronomer",
            "b) A French astronomer",
            "c) A Russian astronomer",
            "d) An American  astronomer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Alstroemeria is an eponym. It is a South American plant named after Swedish naturalist Klas Von Alatroemer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Which of these is an ornamental writing desk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Derrick",
            "b) Boronia",
            "c) Davenport",
            "d) Franciscan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Basket is not an eponym. Bloomers is a women’s loose fitting trousers gathered at the knee. It is named after American women’s rights advocate Amelia. J. Bloomer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which of these is named after an Irish land agent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boolean",
            "b) Derrick",
            "c) Boycott",
            "d) Maxwell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cassegrain Telescope is a reflecting telescope named after the French astronomer N Cassegrain, who devised it. It is an eponym."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an eponym?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chagas Disease",
            "b) Alzheimer’s Disease",
            "c) Marxism",
            "d) Deployment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Davenport is an ornamental writing desk which was made for Captain Davenport. It is an eponym."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Pennsylvania is named after whom?",
        "Options": [
            "a) William Penn",
            "b) Jean Penn",
            "c) Ralph Penn",
            "d) George  Penn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Boycott means to withdraw from social or commercial relations as a protest. It is an eponym named after an Irish land agent Captain Charles C Boycott. "
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of these is named after a German physician?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alzheimer’s Disease",
            "b) Weil’s Disease",
            "c) Chagas Disease",
            "d) Reye’s Syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Deployment is not an eponym. Chagas Disease is named after Brazilian physician Carlos Chagas and Alzheimer’s Disease is named after German neurologist Alois Alzheimer."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of these is a wine bottle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rehoboam",
            "b) Nicotine",
            "c) Roentgenium",
            "d) Timothy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pennsylvania is an eponym. It is named after an  English real estate entrepreneur and philosopher William Penn."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Between which of these words, there is no agreement in concord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gender",
            "b) Number",
            "c) Person",
            "d) Flowers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Concord means an agreement or harmony between words. It governs the relationship of various parts of sentences to one another. "
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used in apposition to a noun?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A verb clause",
            "b) A noun clause",
            "c) A adjective clause",
            "d) A adverb clause"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Grammatically, concord means agreement between words in gender, number, case or person. It governs the relationship of various parts of sentences to one another. "
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Which pronoun is used as an introductory subject?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He",
            "b) She",
            "c) It",
            "d) They"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the statement, “They nominated him chairman.”, the noun chairman and the pronoun they and him  agree in case. "
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of these agree in number and person?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noun",
            "b) Relative pronoun",
            "c) Verb",
            "d) Adverb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Apposition is a relationship between two or more words in which the units are grammatically parallel and have the same referrant. For example: my sister. "
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "In case of double subject, when does verb takes plural form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When both subjects represent same plan.",
            "b) When both subjects are singular.",
            "c) When one of the subjects is plural.",
            "d) When the subject has multiple nouns."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the person whom you are looking for. Here, in this sentence whom is third person singular and in accusative case. "
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "A team of detectives ______ coming to inspect the crime scene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) are",
            "b) were",
            "c) is",
            "d) may"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the phrase, “ This machine “, demonstrative adjective “this” is used which agrees in number with the noun it qualifies."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which of these means to omit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accept",
            "b) Except",
            "c) Acept",
            "d) Exccept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Homophones are words that sound the same but have different meanings and spellings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of these means to influence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Affect",
            "b) Efect",
            "c) Effect",
            "d) Affecct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Except is a preposition or verb which means to leave out or omit. Accept means to receive and is a verb. Both of these are homophones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "______ is the most important city of a country.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capitol",
            "b) Capetol",
            "c) Capital",
            "d) Capitalisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Affect and effect are homophones. Both these words are verbs. Affect means to influence while effect means to bring about. "
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which of these is an adjective?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Course",
            "b) Coaurse",
            "c) Caorse",
            "d) Coarse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Capital is a noun meaning the most important city or town of a country. Capitol is a noun meaning a building, housing a legislative assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of these expresses distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Farther",
            "b) Father",
            "c) Further",
            "d) Ferther"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Coarse is an adjective meaning unrefined or harsh in texture. Course is a noun meaning the route or direction followed by a river or ship. "
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "_____ refers to the second-mentioned thing of two things.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Later",
            "b) Latter",
            "c) Latte",
            "d) Late"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: She writes everyday in her diary. Dairy means a building or room for storage, processing and distribution of milk and milk products. Diary means a book in which one keeps a daily record of events. "
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Which of these is a conjunction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weather",
            "b) Peace",
            "c) Piece",
            "d) Whether"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Farther is an adverb and an adjective, used to express distance or space. Further means a greater expanse of space or time, quality or degree. "
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which of these means a piece of wood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wage",
            "b) Wadge",
            "c) Wedge",
            "d) Wedje"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Later is an adjective. It is the comparative of late and means after some time. Latter refers to the second or second-mentioned of two people or things. "
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Social letters include ______ letters",
        "Options": [
            "a) friendly",
            "b) business",
            "c) formal",
            "d) order"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Broadly, letters can be divided into two types. They are social letters and business letters. Social letters include friendly letters and invitation letters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Friendly",
            "b) Business",
            "c) Application",
            "d) Musical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Specifically, letters can be divided into seven types. These include: friendly letters, business letters, application letters, letters of enquiry, adjustment letters, orders and complaint letters."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of a letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Date",
            "b) Greeting",
            "c) Photo",
            "d) Signature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any letter must have seven parts: The writer’s address, the date, the courteous greeting or salutation, the main contents of the letter, the courteous leave-taking, the signature and the information on the envelope."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of these is used as a form of greeting for business people?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dear Nitin",
            "b) Dear Father",
            "c) Dear Sir",
            "d) Dear Mr.Patel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The writer’s address is placed at the top right hand corner of the first page. The date should be placed just below it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A letter must be written in one single paragraph.",
            "b) A letter must be complete in all respects.",
            "c) A letter must be written in legible handwriting.",
            "d) A letter must be properly punctuated."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The salutation is placed at the extreme left hand of the first page, just below the date. "
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of these is an example of courteous leave taking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yours Sincerely",
            "b) Yours sincerely,",
            "c) Yours sincerely",
            "d) Sincerely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To address business people, we use Dear Sir, Dear Gentleman, etc. We use names when we address friends or family members. "
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Where should the signature of the writer be placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Above the courteous leave taking",
            "b) Below the courteous leave taking",
            "c) Next to the courteous leave taking",
            "d) On the envelope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The incorrect statement is: A letter must be written in one single paragraph. A letter must be divided into paragraphs. A letter must be complete in all respects. "
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What is the information endorsed on the envelope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Name",
            "b) Address",
            "c) Name and address",
            "d) Name and date"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Courteous leave taking is written below the last word of the letter, and to the right side of the page. It always ends with a comma. And only the first letter must be in capital letter."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Whom are friendly letters not written to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relatives",
            "b) Close friends",
            "c) Family members",
            "d) Manufacturers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Friendly letters are written to relatives and close friends. The language of these letters must be simple and  friendly."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of these forms is not used to address people in friendly letters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dear",
            "b) My dear",
            "c) Respected",
            "d) Dearest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Friendly letters can contain many subjects. The order and choice of these subjects would depend on the writer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which form of courteous leave-taking is not used in friendly letters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yours affectionately",
            "b) Yours truly",
            "c) Yours sincerely",
            "d) Your loving son"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The forms of address used in friendly letters are Dear, My dear, Dearest, etc. For example: Dear father or My dear Neha. "
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which of these is not prefixed with any form of courteous leave-taking in friendly letters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With best wishes",
            "b) With kind regards",
            "c) With kindest regards",
            "d) Your regards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The forms of courteous leave-taking may be: Yours affectionately, Your loving son, Yours very sincerely, etc. Yours truly is used in formal letters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Which of these phrases is used to start the main body of a friendly letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It was nice of you to…",
            "b) All the best.",
            "c) Please refer to your letter no…",
            "d) We are pleased to place an order.."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Courteous leave-taking may be prefixed with: With best wishes, With kind regards, With kindest regards, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which of these phrases is used to end the main body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Best wishes to all of you.",
            "b) Thank you very much for your letter.",
            "c) I received your letter today.",
            "d) Thank you for your letter of 6th March."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of friendly letters the following phrases are normally used to start the main body of the letter: I received your letter an hour ago, It was nice of you to.., I just learnt about.., etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Where does the name of the writer come in a formal invitation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top right corner",
            "b) Top left corner",
            "c) Main body of the letter",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A friendly letter’s main body may end with: Please give your parents my respectful regards, Best wishes to all of you, All the best. "
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Where should the date be written in a formal invitation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A formal invitation should be written in third person. It should contain no heading or no salutation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in business letters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polite words",
            "b) Formal words",
            "c) Abbreviations",
            "d) Clear details"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Business letters should be precise and concise. Businessmen are extremely short of time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which of these must not be mentioned in a business letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Information of the quality of the order",
            "b) Name of the firm",
            "c) The mode of payment",
            "d) With regards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Words which are non-standard or usage of slang must be avoided. Abbreviations constitutes non- standard usage. For example, use advertisement instead of advt. "
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Where should the name of the firm be mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right of the page",
            "b) Below the address of the writer",
            "c) Above the address of the writer",
            "d) On the last page of the letter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The mode of payment must be stated in business letters. Also, the way the goods need to be transported has to be mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a mode of address for any letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To a tradesman",
            "b) To a child",
            "c) To a firm",
            "d) To professional men"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A business letter must have clear details of articles required, giving precise information of the quality and quantity you wish to order. Also, the mode of payment has to be mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of these is not used to conclude a business letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yours faithfully",
            "b) Yours truly",
            "c) Yours sincerely",
            "d) With kind regards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name of the firm or businessman to whom the letter is addressed should be written on the first page of the letter to the left of the page, just below the address of the writer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of these should not be present in a business letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The name of firm or businessman",
            "b) The date",
            "c) Business jargon",
            "d) Courteous leave-taking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modes of address vary depending on the person to whom the letter has been addressed: to a tradesman, to a firm or to professional men. "
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "The space to be left from the top is ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 cms",
            "b) 2.5 cms",
            "c) 4 cms",
            "d) 2 cms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Always begin a business letter with “Dear Sir” and conclude with “Yours faithfully”, “Yours truly”, etc.. but not “Yours sincerely”."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Where are the details of enclosures mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beginning of the letter",
            "b) Below the signature column",
            "c) Right-hand side of the letter",
            "d) Main body of the letter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A business letter should be free of business or technical jargon or stereotyped expressions which convey nothing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of these letters are in response to an advertisement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solicited letters",
            "b) Unsolicited letters",
            "c) Letters of enquiry",
            "d) Letters of complaint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A letter of application should have the same form as a business letter. They are of two types. "
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of these letters of application must include a statement of the writer’s age?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For complain",
            "b) For employment",
            "c) For enquiry",
            "d) For adjustment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Letters of application are of two types : Solicited and unsolicited. Solicited letters are in response to an advertisement and unsolicited are written of one’s own accord. "
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Resume is called curriculum vitae in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) India",
            "b) France",
            "c) North America",
            "d) South America"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A letter of application for employment must include a statement of the writer’s age, education and experience."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of these must not be mentioned in your CV?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Out of turn promotions",
            "b) Special recognitions",
            "c) How you helped your previous employer",
            "d) Salary you are looking for"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Unsolicited letters of application are written of one’s own accord. Solicited letters of application are in response to an advertisement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of these details should not be mentioned in your resume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Age",
            "b) Telephone number",
            "c) Health",
            "d) Nationality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Resume is called curriculum vitae in North America but the two have very different formats in the modern day world of job applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Where is the name and address mentioned in a Job- Description CV?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top right corner",
            "b) Top left corner",
            "c) Bottom right corner",
            "d) Bottom left corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is very unprofessional to mention the salary amount that you hope to earn. Also, you must never belittle your previous boss or company while writing to apply for a new job at another company. "
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a skills profile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Career aim",
            "b) Academic achievements",
            "c) Interests",
            "d) Employment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A resume generally consists of details such as: Age, health, martial status, nationality, education, experience and references."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Which of these is mentioned in a bio- data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Career aim",
            "b) Interests",
            "c) Telephone number",
            "d) Date"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name and address of the specimen along with the date is mentioned in the top left corner of the job description CV. The date is mentioned below the name and address. "
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a resume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Address",
            "b) Age",
            "c) Nationality",
            "d) Experience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. References are mentioned in a resume. Resume has other details like age, health, nationality, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "How many references are usually given in a resume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. A skills profile is different from a job description CV. Here, the stress is less on the jobs you have done and more on the skills you have acquired. "
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a job description CV?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Date",
            "b) Name",
            "c) Nationality",
            "d) Education"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Address is not mentioned in a resume. Age, experience, nationality and health is mentioned along with education."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Where is the name and address mentioned in a skills profile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Top right corner",
            "c) Bottom left corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, three references are to be mentioned in a resume. In some cases, more than three can also be mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "How many references are usually given in a bio-data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nationality is not usually mentioned in a job description CV. Name, address and date is mentioned in a job description CV along with education."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a bio-data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Name",
            "b) Address",
            "c) Career aim",
            "d) References"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The name and address is mentioned in the top left corner in a specimen skills profile. Along with this, career aim, employment and experience is mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Resume is a _____ word.",
        "Options": [
            "a) French",
            "b) German",
            "c) Indian",
            "d) American"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, two references are mentioned in a bio-data. In some cases, more than two can also be mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Curriculum vitae is a ____ word.",
        "Options": [
            "a) French",
            "b) German",
            "c) Latin",
            "d) Indian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Career aim is usually mentioned in a skills profile and not in a bio-data. Name, address, telephone number and references are mentioned in a bio-data."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of these are the most common type of business letters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Letters of application",
            "b) Letters of enquiry",
            "c) Letters of order",
            "d) Letters of adjustment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Letters of enquiry are the most common type of business letters. These should be written with due care. They must create the right impression."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of letters of enquiry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General enquiries",
            "b) Personal enquiries",
            "c) Sales related enquiries",
            "d) Status enquiries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Letters of enquiry can be of three types. They are : General enquiries, sales related enquiries and status enquiries."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a letter of enquiry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General enquiry",
            "b) Status enquiry",
            "c) Friendly enquiry",
            "d) Sales related enquiry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Letters of enquiry are of three types: General enquiries, status enquiries and sales related enquiries. Friendly enquiry doesn’t exist. "
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of these seek information regarding purchase of a product?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General enquiry",
            "b) Status enquiry",
            "c) Sales related enquiry",
            "d) Private enquiry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. General enquiry letters do not result in any business return. They are used to accumulate information for business or private research."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "What is the best way to seek information regarding finance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Schools",
            "b) Banks",
            "c) Shops",
            "d) Post office"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Status enquiries seek information regarding the business practice of enterprises. Sales related enquiries seek information regarding purchase of a product. "
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Which of these details is not required in a letter of enquiry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mode of packing",
            "b) Mode of payment",
            "c) Mode of transport",
            "d) Age of owner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sales related enquiries seek information regarding purchase of a product or service. Status enquiries seek information regarding the business practices of enterprises."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Where should the name and address of the firm writing the letter be mentioned in a letter of enquiry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Top right corner",
            "c) Bottom left corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Status enquiries seek information regarding the financial viability and business practices of enterprises. The best way to seek information on matters regarding finance is through banks or financial institutions."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Where should the courteous leave- taking be mentioned on a letter of enquiry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Top right corner",
            "c) Bottom left corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Only relevant details must be stated in a letter of enquiry, such as: the purpose for which the item is required, the mode of payment, the mode of transport, the mode of packing, the expected delivery schedule, etc. The owner’s age isn’t relevant as it won’t influence the business in any way."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Where is the name of the company inviting mentioned in an invitation of quotation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Bottom left corner",
            "c) Top right corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Quotations are letters of enquiry in which an organisation or an individual asks another organisation or individual to quote its or his rates and terms of payment for the goods intended to be purchased. "
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Where is the name of the company which is invited mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Top right corner",
            "c) Bottom left corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The name of the company inviting is mentioned in the top right corner on an invitation of quotation along with the address and date. "
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Where is the courteous leave-taking mentioned in an invitation of quotation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Bottom right",
            "c) Top right",
            "d) Bottom left"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The name of the company which is invited is mentioned in the top left corner in an invitation of quotation  below the address of the inviting party."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "A tender is advertised in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) newspapers",
            "b) business environment",
            "c) domestic markets",
            "d) sellers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The courteous leave-taking is mentioned in the bottom right corner along with signature and designation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a tender?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Date",
            "b) Notice number",
            "c) Sign",
            "d) Designation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Quotations are letters of enquiry and thus are business letters. It is normal to invite quotations from a  large number of sellers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Where is the designation of the authority giving the tender mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top center",
            "b) Bottom left",
            "c) Bottom right",
            "d) Top left"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is a difference between quotations and tenders. A tender is advertised in newspapers, magazines, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Where is the name of the organization mentioned in the tender?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top center",
            "c) Top right",
            "d) Bottom center"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A tender does not have the sign of the authority mentioned in it. It only has the designation mentioned. "
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of these is mentioned in a tender?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Notice number",
            "b) Signature",
            "c) Address of the tenderer",
            "d) Courteous leave-taking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The name of the authority is mentioned in the bottom right corner along with the organization’s name and branch."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Where is the name of the company placing the order mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Top right corner",
            "c) Bottom left corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Orders for goods are placed on a seller after his quotation is accepted. The order must be precise."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Where is the date mentioned in the letter when an order is placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With the address of the company placing the order",
            "b) Below the address of the seller",
            "c) After the salutation",
            "d) Along with the leave-taking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. While placing an order, the quantity of the goods must be stated. The cost at which it is required should also be mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of these should not be mentioned in a letter while placing an order?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Date",
            "b) Address of seller",
            "c) Age of owner",
            "d) Leave taking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name of the company placing the order is mentioned in the top right corner in the letter. The date is mentioned below that. "
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which of these is mentioned in a letter when an order is placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Age of the owner",
            "b) Nationality of the owner",
            "c) Health of the owner",
            "d) Mode of payment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The date is mentioned along with the name of the address of the buyer in the top right corner in a letter when an order is placed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Where is the leave-taking mentioned in an order letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An order letter has the name of the buyer and the seller along with date and courteous leave-taking.  Also the quantity and cost of the order is mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a letter of complaint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Problems in the supply of goods",
            "b) Shortcomings in the supply of goods",
            "c) Features in the supply of goods",
            "d) Fault in the supply of goods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: No personal details are to be mentioned in an order letter. The mode of payment along with the mode of transportation should be mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Where is the address of the company complaining mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left corner",
            "b) Top right corner",
            "c) Bottom left corner",
            "d) Bottom right corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The courteous leave-taking is mentioned in the bottom right corner after the main body of the letter along with signature and designation."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Where is the leave-taking mentioned in a letter of complaint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A letter of complaint states the problems or shortcomings found in the supply of goods. We need to clearly state the faults found in the goods or services. "
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "An adjustment letter usually follows a letter of ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) enquiry",
            "b) application",
            "c) complaint",
            "d) invitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An adjustment letter usually follows a letter of complaint. There is need to rationally assess a letter of complaint to establish whether or not the complaint is justified. "
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Where is the name of the company writing the letter of adjustment mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom  left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Once it is established that the letter of complaint is in order, it must be assessed whether the money can be refunded or not. "
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Where is the date mentioned in the letter of adjustment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With the name of the company which placed the complaint",
            "b) With name of the company writing the letter",
            "c) After the main body of the letter",
            "d) After the leave-taking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Once it is established that the letter of complaint is in order, it must be assessed whether substitute items can be supplied or not. "
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Where is the name and address of the company that complained mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top right",
            "b) Bottom right",
            "c) Top left",
            "d) Bottom left"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The name and address of the company writing the letter of adjustment is mentioned on the top right corner along with the date."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Where is the leave-taking mentioned in the letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The date is mentioned below the name and address of the company writing the letter of adjustment on the top right corner. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "If the letter of complaint is in order, which of these need not be assessed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If money can be refunded",
            "b) If substitute items can be supplied",
            "c) If the damage of the goods was the fault of the owner",
            "d) If the loss can be claimed from the insurance company"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The name and address of the company which has placed the company is mentioned in the top left below the address of the company writing the letter of adjustment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "The fault in a letter of adjustment should be accepted with ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) grace",
            "b) disgrace",
            "c) disapproval",
            "d) clumsiness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The courteous leave-taking is mentioned in the bottom right corner along with signature and designation below the main body of the letter."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "A letter of adjustment must explain ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) excuses",
            "b) lies",
            "c) facts",
            "d) fakeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Once it is established that the letter of complaint is in order it must then be assessed whether the damage or loss of goods was the fault of transporters."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an important feature of a paragraph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length",
            "b) Breadth",
            "c) Unity",
            "d) Coherence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A paragraph gives expression to thoughts in any writing. It has many features like length, unity, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "An average length of sentence in a paragraph should be _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 to 20 words",
            "b) 25 to 30 words",
            "c) 2 to 5 words",
            "d) 5 to 10 words"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A paragraph gives expression to thoughts in any writing. The important features of paragraph are its length, unity, coherence and emphasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a feature of a paragraph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length",
            "b) Unity",
            "c) Incoherence",
            "d) Correctness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A paragraph should contain short sentences. These are preferred. "
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Where should the main idea be put up in a paragraph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the beginning",
            "b) In the middle",
            "c) At the end",
            "d) After the paragraph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An average length of sentence should be about 15 to 20 words. These should be a variety in sentence length. It is better to adopt a range from 3 to 30 words. "
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a paragraph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Courtesy",
            "b) Positive attitude",
            "c) Discriminatory language",
            "d) Politeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A paragraph has six features. They are: length, unity, coherence, emphasis, courtesy and correctness. Out of these the important ones are length, unity, coherence, emphasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a level of language?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formal",
            "b) Public",
            "c) Informal",
            "d) Substandard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main idea should be put up front within a sentence. A writer must decide the emphasis accordingly. The writer should choose words precisely."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a level of language?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formal writing",
            "b) Informal writing",
            "c) Substandard language",
            "d) Formal speaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A paragraph writer should be sincerely tactful, thoughtful and nondiscriminatory. Courteous communication wins hearts of the readers and the listeners."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Which of these is associated with academic pursuits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informal writing",
            "b) Formal writing",
            "c) Personal writing",
            "d) Substandard writing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three levels of language. They are: formal, informal and substandard (or non standard)."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "A proposal is a medium aimed at ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) instruction",
            "b) persuasion",
            "c) prevention",
            "d) advice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A proposal is a plan or suggestion. It is an offer of something."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of these are the largest requesters of proposals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Teachers",
            "b) Governments",
            "c) Business institutions",
            "d) Builders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A proposal is a medium or an instrument aimed at persuasion. A proposal may suggest internal improvement or it can be used to complete a task by others on payment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an objective of proposal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To construct buildings",
            "b) To demolish new structures",
            "c) To install telecommunications",
            "d) To conduct research"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Governments undertake several projects; hence they are the largest requesters of proposals. There are companies having expertise in special tasks, proposals are sent to them."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "The architecture used by Cloud workloads is:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Event-driver",
            "b) Distributed",
            "c) Data-centric",
            "d) Component-based"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are multiple objectives of proposals. Some of them are: To construct buildings, to demolish old  structures, to install telecommunications, to conduct research, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which of these proposals are academic in nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Research proposals",
            "b) Business proposals",
            "c) Personal proposals",
            "d) Musical proposals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Cloud workloads uses a distributed architecture. Failover and scaling are built into the application and it can scale out by adding more instances to the meet the demand."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "When a potential customer is interested in a vendor’s product after casually speaking to the vendor about it, the customer makes a _______.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Personal proposal",
            "b) Informally solicited proposal",
            "c) Formally solicited proposal",
            "d) Unsolicited proposal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Proposals are made to undertake survey for ground water, minerals etc. They are also made to provide training to staff and executives."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which of these proposals are submitted by qualified individuals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Research proposals",
            "b) Business proposals",
            "c) Private  proposals",
            "d) Personal proposals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Proposals are presentations. They are of two types: research proposals and business proposals. Research proposals are purely academic in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Which of these proposals requires fewer parts of content?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long proposals",
            "b) Short proposals",
            "c) Lengthy proposals",
            "d) Research proposals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In such situation, the customers themselves come forward to the vendor and ask for a proposal; and they don’t look at proposals from other vendors who are offering similar products or services, because they are already interested enough in one vendor. Such proposals are informally solicited proposals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of a proposal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First page",
            "b) Outline",
            "c) Complaint",
            "d) Contents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The contents of proposals vary according to their length. There are twelve parts in a proposal like title and first page, outline, proforma, contents, introduction, etc. The objective of a proposal is for there to be an agreement between the customer and the vendor. Cordiality between the two parties is of utmost importance. So, a complaint shouldn’t be in a proposal at all."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of these does the title and first page not include?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brief information of the proposal",
            "b) Name of the institution",
            "c) Nationality of the person submitting the proposal",
            "d) Name of the person submitting the proposal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The title and first page includes the title of the proposal, a brief information of the proposal, name of the institution, name of the person to whom the proposal is submitted and the name of the person submitting the proposal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most important part of the proposal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Title and first page",
            "b) Abstract",
            "c) Contents",
            "d) Experience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Outline is a brief sketch of the proposal. Main features of the proposal are outlined in an abstract form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Where is the proforma placed in a proposal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) After title",
            "b) After contents",
            "c) After introduction",
            "d) After outline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The abstract is an executive summary seeking to gain a quick overview. It speaks for the entire proposal and is the most important part of the proposal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of these is a must for long proposals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proforma",
            "b) Contents",
            "c) Outline",
            "d) Personnel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The proforma should be prepared carefully and inserted after the abstract. It is useful for both the parties."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of these mentions the objectives of the proposal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introduction",
            "b) Contents",
            "c) Purpose of the proposal",
            "d) Scope of the proposal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The content page outlines the contents of the proposal. It shows a list of matters, tables, figures and charts. It is a must for long proposals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which of these parts contains the background information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Personnels",
            "b) Introduction",
            "c) Scope of the proposal",
            "d) Experience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The purpose of the proposal mention clearly the objectives of the proposal. It should be made clear to the authorities that you understand the problem."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of these is attached at the end of a proposal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrastructure",
            "b) Budget estimate",
            "c) Appendices",
            "d) Experience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The proposal should contain background information about the person or institution submitting the proposal. Experience counts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Which part of a proposal talks about the facilities required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Budget estimate",
            "b) Infrastructure",
            "c) Subsidiary matter",
            "d) Scope of the personnel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Additional bulk may be attached at the end. These are also known as appendices. Appendices are usually in the form of charts or graphs. "
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "The word communication is derived from _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) communicare",
            "b) comunnicare",
            "c) comunicare",
            "d) communnicare"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The word communication is derived from the Latin word “communicare” which means “to share”. Man communicates through a sophisticated system of symbols."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Communicare is a _____ word.",
        "Options": [
            "a) French",
            "b) Latin",
            "c) German",
            "d) Indian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The word communication is derived from the Latin word communicare which means to share. It must advance information with affinity."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of these is the triangle of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ABR",
            "b) ARD",
            "c) ARC",
            "d) ARS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A triangle of communication known as the ARC triangle can be formed. Here A stands for Affinity, R for Reality and C for Communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which of these should communication not advance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Information",
            "b) Affinity",
            "c) Reality",
            "d) Personal desires"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Non-verbal communication includes all external stimuli apart from words uttered or written. "
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of these is the greatest means of conveying information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Writing",
            "b) Words",
            "c) Signs",
            "d) Pictures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A communication must advance information along with affinity. It must advance information which is real- both in intellectual and moral sense. "
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "There is a barrier to communication when words are uttered in a ______ sense.",
        "Options": [
            "a) negative",
            "b) positive",
            "c) polite",
            "d) good"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Though a message can be conveyed by means other than words, man’s greatest means of conveying information is through words. Thus very little information can be conveyed without uttering words. "
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an element of non- verbal communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Personal appearance",
            "b) Posture",
            "c) Eye contact",
            "d) Name of the speaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: There is a barrier to communication when words are uttered in a negative sense. The words uttered must be real to the person who is hearing it.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which of these is a main element of non-verbal communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The volume of the speaker",
            "b) Name of the speaker",
            "c) Name of the listener",
            "d) Age of the speaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Personal appearance is an element of non-verbal communication. Some refer to non-verbal communication as body language. "
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most common form of dyadic communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conversation",
            "b) Texting",
            "c) Blogging",
            "d) Writing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Dyadic communication refers to an interaction between two people. One of the most used form of transaction is through speech."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Words must not be uttered with _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) rudeness",
            "b) compassion",
            "c) respect",
            "d) politeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conversation is the most common form of dyadic communication. In it the speaker and listener continuously change roles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "When are disagreements in a conversation relevant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When they advance a lie",
            "b) When they advance with tact intentions",
            "c) When they are done with bad intentions",
            "d) When they are done with rude intentions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Never hold back information while conversing. There may be many reasons to hold back information but deceit, fear or doubts cannot be among them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a conversation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disagreement",
            "b) Compassion",
            "c) Hogging",
            "d) Discussion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Words must not be uttered with rudeness. They must be uttered with respect and compassion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "When should the discussion in a conversation stop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When it turns into an argument",
            "b) When it is boring",
            "c) When one person doesn’t like the other",
            "d) When a third person joins in"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Disagreements in a conversation are relevant provided they advance the truth and they are done with tact and good intentions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Which of these statements is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continue the topic no matter what the attitude of the other person is.",
            "b) Respect other person’s time and interest.",
            "c) Don’t utter the name of the opposite person  frequently.",
            "d) We can use words even if have a vague understanding of it."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Avoid hogging the conversation, simply because conversation means exchange of views. Speak something relevant even in a social conversation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "____ should be avoided in a conversation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard words",
            "b) Slang",
            "c) Name of the other person",
            "d) Truth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Always discuss a topic, but hold yourself back if a conversation relegates into an argument.  Wise men discuss while fools argue. "
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "When should the topic be altered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the listener’s attitude is positive",
            "b) When you don’t like the appearance of the other person",
            "c) When the listener likes the topic",
            "d) When the listener’s attitude is negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Respect other person’s time and interest. The words uttered must convey precise meaning. We shouldn’t use words without knowing their meaning. "
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of these is not considered in a telephonic conversation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The tone of the speaker",
            "b) The volume of the speaker",
            "c) Body language",
            "d) The emotional content of the communication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two people involved in a telephonic conversation are unable to see each other. Hence, the body language of the speakers isn’t very important. However, the doesn’t take away from the fact that a telephonic conversation is a full-fledged conversation for which most other parameters of a dyadic exchange hold true. "
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "After about how many rings should the telephone be lifted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A telephonic conversation should be brief and to the point. A telephone is not meant for gossiping. "
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "What is the first thing you must utter when you pick up a call?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Your name and designation",
            "b) Who is calling?",
            "c) Why did you call?",
            "d) What do you want?"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is a distinct rhythm about receiving telephone calls. The receiver must be lifted promptly, at best after one or two rings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of these should be kept in mind while receiving a call?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Be rude, if the caller is rude.",
            "b) If the information is not readily available, take his phone number and call back.",
            "c) A message can be noted in hints",
            "d) You can be rude to a person if it’s a wrong connection."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first thing you must do is utter your full name and designation. After your own introduction, ask the caller to reveal his name and designation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Which of these should be kept in mind while giving instructions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The pitch of the receiver",
            "b) The tone of the receiver",
            "c) His ability to grasp information",
            "d) The physical condition of the receiver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case the information is not readily available, take his phone number and call back. Be warm and friendly even when the caller is rude. "
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Delegation of responsibility must be done with _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) empathy",
            "b) rudeness",
            "c) dominance",
            "d) disrespect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. While making a call, have all relevant information ready before hand. It is rude and silly to search for material in the files when somebody is already on the line. "
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "An instruction must be followed by ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) spoken reply",
            "b) written reply",
            "c) action",
            "d) sign"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When giving instructions, keep in mind : the mental and emotional built up of the receiver, his ability to grasp information and act upon the instructions given to him. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "A person who meets the media must have greater _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) restraint",
            "b) honesty",
            "c) agitation",
            "d) aggressiveness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Delegation of responsibility or asking others to carry out a task must be done with compassion and empathy. It is best to entrust one job at a time to a person. "
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Which of these causes a problem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intellectual freedom",
            "b) Moral bondage",
            "c) First  hand life",
            "d) Cultural exchange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A society is a voluntary organisation where human beings come together for convenience. "
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Communication must advance ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) moral bondage",
            "b) intellectual fraud",
            "c) emotional trap",
            "d) inspiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The best way to live life is first hand and to let others live their lives first hand as well. People who live first hand acknowledge truth from others and are rarely bothered with false criticism. "
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Language should never encroach on which of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) intellectual fraud",
            "b) intellectual privacy",
            "c) intellectual bondage",
            "d) moral bondage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is no need to be critical of others, no matter how foolish it may appear to you. Two people may exist mutually in intellectual freedom. The problem arises when we seek moral bondage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most common form of condemnation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Religion based",
            "b) Caste based",
            "c) Personal prejudices",
            "d) Status based"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The statement is: Communication must advance compassion and inspiration. Our social language must never be so arranged as to emotionally trap others. "
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Language must advance _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) inspiration",
            "b) truth",
            "c) intellectual fraud",
            "d) emotional trap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Language should never encroach on intellectual privacy. Those who talk of privacy rarely think of intellectual privacy as well. Everyone needs intellectual privacy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of these should be invoked through words?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compassion",
            "b) hostility",
            "c) spitefulness",
            "d) rudeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We must never condemn on the basis of religion, caste, colour, status or personal prejudices. The last form of condemnation is the most common. "
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a second hand emotion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Honour",
            "b) Prestige",
            "c) Creativity",
            "d) Reputation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Language must advance truth and compassion. Truth can become a rare commodity if we do not know the precise meaning of words. "
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "People who live life first hand, know the path of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) truth",
            "b) reputation",
            "c) fame",
            "d) money"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compassion and positive emotions should be invoked through words, otherwise there may be a need to reassess their efficacy. It is better to err on the positive rather than the negative side. "
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Around which of these is culture not centered for a modern man?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organisation",
            "b) Club",
            "c) Temple",
            "d) Society"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Culture is a rather loose term. To a religious man, culture is centered entirely around the place of worship."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Any group must advance strength through _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) debate",
            "b) unity",
            "c) speech",
            "d) dyadic communication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To a religious man, culture is centered entirely around the place of worship. To a modern man it may be centered around the club, organisation, society or group."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "An organisation must give _____ to an individual.",
        "Options": [
            "a) freedom",
            "b) work load",
            "c) punishment",
            "d) limitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Any group must advance strength through unity and not have the ugliness of a collective, where a vague illusion of a collective throttles individual freedom. "
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a club?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basic courtesies",
            "b) Club timings",
            "c) Dress code",
            "d) Rude behavior"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An organisation must enhance individual joy and freedom; it must not reduce them. A collective must have least possible amount of rules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Language in the club must enhance ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) debates",
            "b) fights",
            "c) harmony",
            "d) disagreement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Clubs are recreational institutions. Members must use them for recreation and let others use them for their recreation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a cultural event?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joy",
            "b) Culture",
            "c) Relaxation",
            "d) Personal envy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Members must show basic courtesies while they are in the club. They must adhere to the club timings and its dress code. Children must be left at home in case they are not allowed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which of these must not be used while addressing a woman?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mrs. Verma",
            "b) Miss Sharma",
            "c) Miss",
            "d) Bhabhiji"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Language in the club must enhance harmony. In the case of clubs meant for cultural activities or games, it is better to participate in them."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided when with a woman?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non standard words",
            "b) Offering to buy her a drink",
            "c) Getting her a seat",
            "d) Praising her"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Our words and actions must spread harmony and joy. The intention should be one of accommodation and genuine caring instead of personal envy and resentment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "What is the dress code for a normal cultural event?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formal wear",
            "b) Party wear",
            "c) Home wear",
            "d) Beach wear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. A cultural event is different from office because participation in it is voluntary. Yet, these events also have their rules which must be adhered to. "
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided at a cultural event?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relaxation",
            "b) Arguing",
            "c) Socialising",
            "d) Organizing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The clothes at a cultural event should be formal and relaxed unless the occasion demands otherwise. It would be foolish to arrive at a beach party in a suit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which of these points need not be considered for a debate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Availability of precise information",
            "b) Age of opponent",
            "c) Fluency in language",
            "d) Body language"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is bad manners to enter into heated arguments in such events. These create a vitiated atmosphere and ruins everyone’s mood. A healthy debate, on the other hand is a politer way to voice your views without offending anybody. "
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Which of these is not considered for a debate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Availability of information",
            "b) Fluency in language",
            "c) Body language",
            "d) Volume of the speaker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three points are to be considered before one goes for a debate. The first and foremost thing is the availability of authentic and precise information regarding the subject on which the debate is to be held. The second point is your fluency in language and third is your body language. "
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of these are to be avoided in a debate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fights",
            "b) Listening",
            "c) Taking notes",
            "d) Using rhetoric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Three things are to be considered in a debate : availability of authentic and precise information regarding the subject, fluency in the language and the adequate use of body language. "
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of these debates is on-spot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extempore",
            "b) In advance",
            "c) Written",
            "d) Personal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Same rules apply for effective writing and oral presentation. What holds good for effective writing applies equally to oral presentation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informative",
            "b) Personal",
            "c) Persuasive",
            "d) Special occasion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fights and arguments must be avoided in a debate. A few devices like rhetoric may be used to make the speech more forceful and effective."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a quality of a good debater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Taking notes",
            "b) Listening",
            "c) Interrupting their opponent’s speech",
            "d) Answering cross questions with confidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A debate can be of two types : with a topic given in advance or extempore. In the case when the topic is given in advance, it is worthwhile to construct a message carefully. "
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "A ______ speaker looks into the eyes of the audience.",
        "Options": [
            "a) confident",
            "b) impatient",
            "c) rude",
            "d) impolite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is best to look straight into the eyes of the audience. This would convince the audience that you are a confident speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of these may convey arrogance ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jointed finger tips",
            "b) A shoulder shrug",
            "c) A pointed finger",
            "d) Hands swinging loosely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jointed finger tips convey surety and confidence, if done properly. They may convey arrogance, if done badly. A shoulder shrug may convey sincerity or callousness."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "The tone of the speaker should be _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) loud",
            "b) clear",
            "c) low",
            "d) soft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A pointed finger may be deemed to be a gesture of accusation or forcefulness. While approaching to the rostrum it is best to walk in a forceful manner with hands swinging loosely by the side."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "During practice, by how much should the speech be lengthened?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 5 %",
            "b) 6 to 10 %",
            "c) 7 to 11 %",
            "d) 9 to 13 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tone of the speaker should be clear and precise. A good speaker always pauses on punctuation marks and when he wishes to drive home a point. "
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "A speech must be prepared with _______ in mind.",
        "Options": [
            "a) the result",
            "b) praise",
            "c) an audience",
            "d) admiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is better to make a speech lengthier by 2 to 5 percent in practice, since when crunch time arrives the best speaker tends to speak faster or forget some lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "A speech must advance _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) dishonesty",
            "b) truth",
            "c) aggressiveness",
            "d) negativity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A speech must be prepared with an audience in mind. It must give facts and clearly mention in case opinions are made. "
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which of these is important in having mutual understanding with colleagues?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective listening",
            "b) Speaking",
            "c) Talking",
            "d) Writing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A speech must advance the truth and not convolute truth by irritating people. Wit and humour are an integral part of any speech but they must not be biting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of these does not enhance listening skills?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attention",
            "b) Frankness",
            "c) Clear perception",
            "d) Ignoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Effective listening is extremely important in having mutual understanding with colleagues, superiors and subordinates. Listening is an important part of communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Which of these are vital for any organisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Debates",
            "b) Group discussions",
            "c) Speeches",
            "d) Arguments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Group discussions are vital for any organisation. They streamline stray thoughts in a potent proactive action and generate information."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of these qualities are important in a group discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emotional stability",
            "b) Hostility",
            "c) Ignorance",
            "d) Aggressiveness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Emotional stability plays an important role in a group discussion. No organisation wants a person who is not in control of his emotions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "In a group discussion, one must communicate with ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hostility",
            "b) Ignorance",
            "c) knowledge",
            "d) long sentences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a group discussion, one must communicate with knowledge. He must be polite and compassionate and must utter ideas which are real to those present and easily understood."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "When is the worst time to break into a discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When everyone is silent",
            "b) When one person is talking",
            "c) When two or three people are talking simultaneously",
            "d) When there is less time left"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. In a group discussion, the discussion must be directed to its logical conclusion. You must appear to neatly direct a discussion to its logical conclusion without appearing to be superior to the offending person. "
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "A group discussion must advance _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) truth",
            "b) dishonesty",
            "c) Personal glory",
            "d) arguments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is crucial to know when to break into a discussion. The worst time to break into a discussion is when two or three people are discussing a topic and talking simultaneously. "
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in a group discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speaking facts",
            "b) Asking questions",
            "c) Speaking fast",
            "d) Speaking with clarity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is: A group discussion must advance truth. A group discussion is not meant for personal glory. It is meant to advance certain aspects to their logical conclusion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "In a group discussion, we should be _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) assertive",
            "b) dominating",
            "c) subjective",
            "d) ignorant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We must speak about facts and with clarity. We must never mumble, shout or speak very fast. It is better to ask questions in case a point is not understood."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which of these factors do not enhance listening skills?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attention",
            "b) Clear perception",
            "c) Fakeness",
            "d) Frankness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a group discussion we must be assertive. There is no room for dominating others. There is no place for subjectivity or personal prejudices. "
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most important tool of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Body language",
            "b) Gestures",
            "c) Language",
            "d) Posture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Language is the most important tool of communication. The word communication is derived from the Latin word “communicare”, which means to share. Body language, posture and gestures are also important tools of communication; but they are secondary to language.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in any presentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proper grammar",
            "b) Complex words",
            "c) Short sentences",
            "d) Clear voice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In any presentation, we should use proper grammar. We should use short sentences and simple and proper words. There should be used of clear good voice. "
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of these is not important in an oral presentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Words",
            "b) Body language",
            "c) Gestures",
            "d) The number of people as audience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Oral presentations are an integral part of an engineer’s career. He has to take part in meetings, conferences and seminars. "
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Which of these is the best way to establish a proper rapport with audience?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pointing a finger",
            "b) Making eye contact",
            "c) Waving your hands",
            "d) Standing erect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Words are crucial, but they are not the only thing which is important. Body language, which includes a person’s demeanour, posture and gestures, is important as well. "
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "In an oral presentation, the speaker should not _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) panic",
            "b) pause",
            "c) make eye contact",
            "d) inspire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The best way to establish a proper rapport with the audience is by establishing eye contact. It is vital to look at the audience straight in the eye with confidence."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Which of these is a sign of under confidence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speaking and naturally shifting your eyes around",
            "b) Transfixed on one face",
            "c) Pointing your finger",
            "d) Using your hands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are times when you may forget your lines. There is no need to panic. Panic can result in further errors. The idea is to gracefully pick up the loose ends from the script held in front of you. "
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of these is the best pace to utter a speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 words per minute",
            "b) 150 words per minute",
            "c) 200 words per minute",
            "d) 250 words per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While speaking, gently and naturally shifting your eyes all around so that it appears as if you are interested in all those who are present. Please don’t be transfixed on one face. It is a sign of under- confidence."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used to break the monotony in a speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Humour",
            "b) Constant tone",
            "c) Low voice",
            "d) Sad story"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The best pace to utter a speech is to convey about 150 words per minute. Please don’t make illogical sounds like er or ah. "
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "A speech must always present _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) facts",
            "b) opinions",
            "c) suggestions",
            "d) perspectives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A speech must always present facts, which are very different from opinions. The two must never be confused. "
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided by the speaker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He must convey precise information.",
            "b) He must ensure that the information is understood by the audience.",
            "c) He must inspire the audience to totally accept his point of view.",
            "d) He must force the audience to totally accept his point of view."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main job of the speaker is three fold : He must convey precise information, he must ensure that the information is understood by the audience and he must inspire the audience to totally accept his point of view."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which of these is required to convey large information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voice",
            "b) Tone",
            "c) Body land",
            "d) Preparation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Masquerading opinions as facts amounts to perpetrating an intellectual fraud. We must present facts, or we must let the audience know that we are presenting our personal opinions."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided by a speaker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abstract words",
            "b) Short sentences",
            "c) Good pronunciation",
            "d) Steady pace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. One should take one’s time while giving a presentation, but at the same time, they shouldn’t be too slow. A slow pace tends to break the attention of the audience and bore them out. The pace shouldn’t be too fast either, otherwise the audience will not have the time to grasp the crux of the presentation. There should be used of a steady pace, which is neither too fast nor too slow. "
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of these is a sign of rude manners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Staring at the floor",
            "b) Making eye contact",
            "c) Steady pace",
            "d) Simple words"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A good speech is rarely made extempore. No speaker can convey large amounts of information without adequate preparation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a group discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) listening",
            "b) shouting",
            "c) speaking",
            "d) writing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Abstract words must be avoided in a speech. There must be used of familiar words. Also there must be used of short sentence with a steady pace."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in a speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Illogical sounds",
            "b) Gestures",
            "c) Eye contact",
            "d) Interest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Please do not be transfixed on one face, or stare at the ceiling or floor. This is a sign, either of under confidence or of rude manners. "
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "A finger may be used to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) show over confidence",
            "b) inspire",
            "c) show under confidence",
            "d) appoint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a group discussion, we must never mumble, shout or speak very fast. To enhance listening ability, one should note down the vital points made by the speaker in his or her speech. "
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used to overcome stage fear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A speech must be prepared with care.",
            "b) A speech must be untimed.",
            "c) Facts need not be checked.",
            "d) There should be no pause."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Every speaker has a natural stage of fear. This can be overcome by various means like : a speech must be prepared with care and must be learnt properly."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Which of these is not advisable to make facts interesting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By narrating them as a story",
            "b) Through an anecdote",
            "c) With the help of a personal incident",
            "d) By stating them as points"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Facts should be presented in an interesting manner. Most speakers resort to narrating a story or an anecdote to ensure the interest of the audience."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "There are how many ways to start a presentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A speaker must have a positive and confident attitude. This would ensure the empathy of the audience."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "In ______ approach, the speaker introduces the company and the product.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hard sell",
            "b) soft sell",
            "c) rough sell",
            "d) smooth sell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two ways in which a presentation can be started. They are: Hard sell approach and soft sell approach. "
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "In any meeting, the most worthwhile impact is made by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) stories",
            "b) incidents",
            "c) facts",
            "d) anecdotes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. In hard sell approach, the speaker begins with a question or a remark which establishes the requirement of the customer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of these can irritate the audience?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If facts are uttered coherently",
            "b) If facts are uttered incoherently",
            "c) Narrating incidents",
            "d) Narrating anecdotes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: In soft sell approach, the speaker introduces the company and the product. "
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which of these represent defiance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clenched fist",
            "b) Clinton thumb",
            "c) Fig sign",
            "d) Dap greeting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In any meeting, the most worthwhile impact is made by facts. The more profound the facts the greater is the impact that a speaker would leave in a meeting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Which of these does not mean stage fear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) aphonia",
            "b) phonia",
            "c) aphonia clericorum",
            "d) aphonia paralytica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If facts are uttered incoherently or without cohesion, there is a likelihood that the audience would be irritated rather than be pleased. "
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "In a ________ , each member speaks on a pre-planned subject.",
        "Options": [
            "a) seminar",
            "b) conference",
            "c) panel discussion",
            "d) symposium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A seminar discusses in a small group on original research or advanced study through oral or written reports. "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "In which of these people with similar interests contribute with their knowledge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) seminar",
            "b) conference",
            "c) symposium",
            "d) convention"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. In a symposium, a small group of experts discuss different aspects of a problem for the benefit of an audience. "
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "A ______ is a fellowship meeting of a fraternal group.",
        "Options": [
            "a) conference",
            "b) symposium",
            "c) seminar",
            "d) convention"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: In a panel discussion, each member speaks on a pre-planned subject, which is normally in the form of a question."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which of these is not used to organise a seminar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oral reports",
            "b) Written reports",
            "c) Exchange of ideas",
            "d) Recommendations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a conference, people with similar interests contribute with their knowledge. It ends in a set of suggestions or recommendations which are based on the central theme of the conference. "
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "A conference is not attended by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) invited guests",
            "b) common people",
            "c) permitted observers",
            "d) people with common interests"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A convention is a fellowship meeting of a fraternal group. Only matters of professional interest are discussed in it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "We learn maximum by _____.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hearing",
            "b) seeing",
            "c) speaking",
            "d) feeling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A seminar discusses in a small group on original research or advanced study through oral or written reports. It may also be organised through exchange of ideas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in a meeting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Patience",
            "b) Tact",
            "c) Leadership",
            "d) Criticism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a conference, people with similar interests contribute with their knowledge. A conference is only attended by invited guests or permitted observers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Before the meeting is concluded, there must be a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) summary",
            "b) question",
            "c) discussion",
            "d) agenda"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hearing is not the most crucial learning sensory perception available to man. A mere 11% of the knowledge that we pick us is through hearing. The eyes account for nearly 83% of our learning. "
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of these points need not be mentioned in a notice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Name",
            "b) Address of company",
            "c) Age",
            "d) Date"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are seven points which are to be mentioned in a notice. They are : Name, address and contact details of company, date, heading, notice details, name and designation, enclosure and to details.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which of these is the first thing mentioned in a notice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Name of the organization",
            "b) Date",
            "c) Notice",
            "d) Notice details"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first point mentioned in the notice is the name of the organization along with its address and contact details like phone number, email id, website, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Where is the date mentioned in a notice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The date is mentioned in the top right corner in a notice below the name and details of the organization and above the heading “Notice”."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Where is the name and designation of the authority mentioned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The name and designation of the concerned authority is mentioned in the bottom right corner below the notice details and above the enclosure details.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Which of these details is not mentioned in the main notice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Date",
            "c) Venue",
            "d) Name of the speakers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main notice includes the name and details of the event or meeting and other details like date, time, venue and enclosures if any. "
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Where is the date mentioned in a minutes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a minutes, the date is mentioned at the end in the bottom left corner below the signature and designation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which of these details are not mentioned in minutes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Venue of the meeting",
            "b) Date of the meeting",
            "c) Name of the chairman",
            "d) Age of the chairman"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Minutes must be self-sufficient records. They must have details like the name of the organization, day, date and time of meeting, venue, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Where is the signature of the Secretary mentioned in minutes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Minutes must have the following details: Name of organisation, day and date of the meeting, venue of the meeting, name of the chairman, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Which of these do not deal with precise information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engineer",
            "b) Scientist",
            "c) Technician",
            "d) Fiction writer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A scientist, engineer, technician or technologist deals with precise information. A fiction writer may indulge in charming nonsense, but a scientific man must develop a style of writing which conveys information with precision. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "In an office, an employee communicates horizontally with his _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) superiors",
            "b) subordinates",
            "c) colleagues",
            "d) assistant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: In an office, an employee communicates horizontally with his colleagues. Horizontal communication happens between people who are on the same tier as each other in an office hierarchy. He communicates vertically with his subordinates and superiors. Vertical communication happens between people who are on different levels in an office hierarchy."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Talking comes under which type of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verbal",
            "b) Non- verbal",
            "c) Written",
            "d) Dramatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Communication can be of two types. They are: verbal communication and non-verbal communication. Talking is an effective tool, but it has limited reach. "
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Which of these has maximum reach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Writing",
            "b) Listening",
            "c) Speaking",
            "d) Talking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Writing has enormous reach. It has an inviolable quality about it, since what has been written cannot be altered. "
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "How is good technical writing achieved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Naturally",
            "b) By practice",
            "c) Listening",
            "d) Speaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Good technical writing does not come naturally. It is an end product of careful practice. It is obvious that a technical writer must have something substantial to say. "
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Which of these parameters are not required to define style?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moral truth",
            "b) Compassion",
            "c) Gender",
            "d) Information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three parameters that are stated when defining style. They are: moral truth, compassion and information with precision. "
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "A writer must not convey information with _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) precision",
            "b) clarity",
            "c) randomness",
            "d) truth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Any style must convey intellectual and moral truth. Most writers tend to hide truth. Their language becomes a vehicle of ambiguity."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Which of these are to be avoided in any style of writing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Truth",
            "b) Clarity",
            "c) Compassion",
            "d) Dishonesty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Any writer must convey truth with warmth and compassion. Any good writing must create a bond of oneness between writer and reader. "
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Technical writing demands ______ use of language.",
        "Options": [
            "a) figurative",
            "b) poetic",
            "c) factual",
            "d) dramatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Technical writing is different from general writing. It deals with pure or applied sciences. It is not the same as general writing, which involves putting down one’s thoughts and opinions on any relevant topic in the form of meaningful, coherent writing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in technical writing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Facts",
            "b) Grammar",
            "c) Punctuation",
            "d) Personal feelings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Technical writing needs accuracy of expression and a restraint in style. It demands factual use of language. It does not care for figurative or poetic impressions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Which of these words is used in technical writing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Apex",
            "b) Top",
            "c) Slanting",
            "d) Bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Technical writing must be as objective as possible. There is no place for personal feelings in technical writing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which of these is a technical word for slanting ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral",
            "b) Sloping",
            "c) Tilting",
            "d) Bent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Technical writing uses many special words. Thus a science book may use the word apex instead of top, base instead of  bottom, etc.. "
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "A scientist gets his special words from ____ language.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Latin",
            "b) English",
            "c) French",
            "d) Italian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Technical writing uses special words instead of general words. Therefore , lateral is used instead of slanting, apex instead of top, base instead of bottom, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Trigonometry is a ____ word.",
        "Options": [
            "a) French",
            "b) German",
            "c) Indian",
            "d) Greek"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. We should use the familiar words instead of the abstract word in technical writing. In technical writing, the facts conveyed take priority over the level of vocabulary used. For instance, it is better to use to get instead of to acquire."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Which of these means bioscope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Math",
            "b) Science",
            "c) Cinema",
            "d) Binoculars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A scientist gets his special words from Greek and Latin languages. These languages provide huge opportunities to scientists to create new words."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Electricity is derived from _____ language.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indian",
            "b) Greek",
            "c) French",
            "d) Italian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Trigonometry is a Greek word. It means : tri = three, gon = angle, metre = measure. Thus Trigonometry is a study of the relationships between the three angles of the triangle. "
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a medium for e-mail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intranet",
            "b) Internet",
            "c) Extranet",
            "d) Paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: E-mail and websites are transmitted through Intranet, Internet and extranet. Everything has gone electronic way. "
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of these defined the internet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Federal Networking Council",
            "b) The Federal Network Council",
            "c) The Federal Networking Committee",
            "d) The Federal Network Committee"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Federal Networking Council in 1995 passes a unanimous resolution to define internet. Internet refers to a global information system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which of these is not used by intranet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TCP",
            "b) BSNL",
            "c) IP",
            "d) HTTP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Intranet is a company’s internal web and uses TCP/IP, HTTP and other internet protocols. It’s main object is to share company information among employees."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of these is the easiest way of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E-mail",
            "b) Telephone",
            "c) Fax",
            "d) Letter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Extranet is a web within a web. Extranet is a collaborative network which uses internet protocols for business purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of these do not provide free E-mail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hotmail",
            "b) Rediff",
            "c) WhatsApp",
            "d) Yahoo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Intranet is a company’s internal web and uses TCP/IP, HTTP and other internet protocols. It’s main object is to share company information among employees."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in an E-mail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wrong E-mail address",
            "b) Subject line",
            "c) Smileys",
            "d) Re-reading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Billions of E-mail messages are sent throughout the world today. It is the cheapest and convenient than any other forms of communication like telephone or fax."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which of these terms do not need a definition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Principles",
            "b) Concepts",
            "c) Processes",
            "d) Names"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Information is required to describe an object. It is also needed to explain processes involved in technical operations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "A definition usually consists of ___ statement(s).",
        "Options": [
            "a) three",
            "b) one",
            "c) four",
            "d) five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Terms which involve principles, concepts or processes need to be defined. It is done so that ambiguities can be removed and information can be made available to others."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "A definition consists of how many parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A definition usually consists of one statement, though more than one statement might sometimes be necessary. "
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of these must be eliminated by a writer while defining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Facts",
            "b) Knowledge",
            "c) Prejudices",
            "d) Information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A definition must contain: The class to which the term belongs and the thing which separates it from other members of the same class. "
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of these is a representation of an object drawn by lines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drawing",
            "b) Picture",
            "c) Illustration",
            "d) Photo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A definition excludes everything which is unimportant, but without taking away anything from the main information that needs to be conveyed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "A _____ is a representation of an object on another surface.",
        "Options": [
            "a) drawing",
            "b) image",
            "c) illustration",
            "d) picture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While defining something a writer must eliminate his prejudices and limitations of knowledge in that field. He must give an objective and complete definition of a term."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "What does LASER stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Light Amplification of Stimulated Emission of Radiation",
            "b) Light Amplification of Stimulated Emission by Radiation",
            "c) Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation",
            "d) Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission by Radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A drawing is a representation of an object drawn by lines, shade, etc..A picture is different from a drawing and an illustration."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Thermostat is a combination of ___ and ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) therm, ostat",
            "b) thermo, stat",
            "c) therm, stat",
            "d) therms, tat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A picture is a representation of an object on another surface. A drawing is a representation of an object drawn by lines, shade, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Which of these is not used in technical writing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equations",
            "b) Abbreviations",
            "c) Poetic devices",
            "d) References"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A technical description is used to describe an object or a process. Science and technology must convey facts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a step in the technical description of an object?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Definition of object",
            "b) General description of object",
            "c) Age of writer",
            "d) Description of components of objects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any technical writing must have a distinct look. Technical writing may use equations, abbreviations, numerals, references, tables, illustrations etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Telex is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Teleprinter Exchange Service",
            "b) Telephone Exchange Service",
            "c) Teleprinter Engine Service",
            "d) Telephone Engine Service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. While writing technical descriptions of objects , the object must be defined first. Next, the manner in which the object works must be described. "
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "In which step is the general description of the object given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) One",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are four steps in the technical description of an object : Definition of the object, manner in which the object works, general description of the object and a description of the important components of the object."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": " _____ helps a reader to arrive at a conclusion whether the method of performing is efficient.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A process",
            "b) An object",
            "c) A trick",
            "d) A description"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Telex is a Teleprinter Exchange Service furnished to subscribers locally and internationally. It is similar to a type writer but it functions over electric wires. "
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a step in the technical description of a process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introduction",
            "b) Conclusion",
            "c) Complaining",
            "d) Listing of main steps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are four steps in the technical description of an object: Definition of the object, manner in which the object works, general description of the object and a description of the important components of the object."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Which of these is not listed in the introduction of technical description of a process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Statement of process",
            "b) Reason to perform the process",
            "c) Main steps",
            "d) List of tools"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A process helps a reader to arrive at a conclusion whether the method of performing is efficient and reliable or not."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "In which step are the main steps of a process explained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are four steps in the technical description of a process. They are: Introduction, listing of main steps, explanation of each step and conclusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of these is a  set of instructions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Report",
            "b) Letter",
            "c) Notice",
            "d) Operating manual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A machine carries an operating manual. This is a list of instructions to a person who wishes to operate the machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Which of these does not have an operating manual?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Televisions",
            "b) Telephones",
            "c) Pens",
            "d) Washing machines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An operating manual is a list of step-by-step instructions to assist a person in operating a particular machine. Operating manuals exist for household goods like washing machines, televisions, air-conditioners and so on. One doesn’t need a manual to know how to use a pen."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in an instruction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ambiguity",
            "b) Less words",
            "c) Precision",
            "d) Clarity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. An operating manual is different from a repairing manual. A technical instruction must fulfill the purpose for which it is written."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "A technical instruction must begin with _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) an introduction",
            "b) a figure",
            "c) a drawing",
            "d) a warning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An instruction must state facts precisely and in as few words as is possible. It must be free from ambiguity and it must be imperative."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used for better understanding of an instruction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longer sentences",
            "b) Figures",
            "c) Ambiguity",
            "d) Complex words"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A technical instruction must begin with an introduction which must tell the reader about the process and what needs to be done."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which of these is advisable for instructions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long sentences",
            "b) Detailed information",
            "c) Imperative sentences",
            "d) Complex sentences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A technical instruction must be free from ambiguity and it must be imperative. Figures, drawings and photographs may be used to achieve better understanding. "
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Which is the last step in a technical instruction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introduction",
            "b) Steps",
            "c) Drawing",
            "d) Conclusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Warnings against misuse or wrong use should be included to prevent damage or loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of these words can be used for omission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normally",
            "b) er",
            "c) etc",
            "d) Generally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is advisable to use imperative sentences. Instead of saying “The apparatus should be washed.”, it is better to say “Wash the apparatus.“"
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of these reports are used in business?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formal technical reports",
            "b) Informal reports",
            "c) Personal reports",
            "d) Musical reports"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Technical reports are of two types. They are: formal and non- formal technical reports. They must present a complete picture of all the necessary and relevant facts."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Which of these forms is not used to write a non-formal report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filling in a blank form",
            "b) App",
            "c) Form of a letter",
            "d) Memorandum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Technical reports may be formal or non- formal. Non- formal reports may be written in one of the three forms: By filling in a blank form, form of a letter or form of a memorandum. "
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a method of writing a non-formal letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filling in a blank form",
            "b) Form of a letter",
            "c) Form of a memorandum",
            "d) Formal of a notice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A non- formal technical report may be written by filling in a blank form, printed for a particular purpose. "
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "A non- formal report written in the form of a letter is similar to a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) friendly letter",
            "b) business letter",
            "c) complaint letter",
            "d) notice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A non- formal technical report may be written in three forms. They are: by filling in a blank form, printed for a particular purpose. "
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Which of these forms does a formal report not take?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Essay",
            "b) Pamphlet",
            "c) Friendly letter",
            "d) Book"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A non- formal technical report written in the form of a letter is similar to a normal business letter. In the case of report a subject heading is added before salutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of a report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Periodic",
            "b) Progress",
            "c) Trouble",
            "d) Fancy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A memorandum is almost like a letter. It must be used when information is to be passes within a particular organisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Which of these reports contains information of a routine nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Periodic report",
            "b) Progress report",
            "c) Trouble report",
            "d) Laboratory report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A formal report is long. It takes the form of an essay, pamphlet or book. It is always written in an impersonal tone."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "______ report includes breakdown of machinery.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feasibility",
            "b) Periodic",
            "c) Trouble",
            "d) Progress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are five types of reports. They are: periodic report, progress report, laboratory report, feasibility report and trouble report."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Which of these does not come under reports?",
        "Options": [
            "a) News items",
            "b) Memorandums",
            "c) Notice",
            "d) Report cards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A report is a systematic description of an event for someone who was not present on the scene."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a parameter of a formal report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Presentation",
            "b) Complaint",
            "c) Information",
            "d) Request"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A report is a systematic description of an event for someone who was not present on the scene. Most memorandums and news items thus come in the category of reports. A notice doesn’t fall under this category as it is usually very briefly worded."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Which of these people submit business-like reports?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Business administrators",
            "b) Teachers",
            "c) Engineers",
            "d) Scientists"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three parameters for a formal report. They are: presentation, information and request from an authorised person."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "A ______ report provides information on scientific tests carried out by engineers or scientists.",
        "Options": [
            "a) progress",
            "b) periodic",
            "c) laboratory",
            "d) trouble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A formal report must contain rational information. It should be presented in an organised manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Which of these reports is written before starting a new project?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feasibility report",
            "b) Periodic report",
            "c) Trouble report",
            "d) Progress report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reports which business administrators, engineers and scientists write in course of their routine work are end products of diligent analysis, profound mental activity and rational conclusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of these reports lists down precautions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progress report",
            "b) Periodic report",
            "c) Trouble report",
            "d) Feasibility report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A laboratory report provides information on tests carried out in a laboratory. They are submitted by engineers or scientists. "
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "In which of these cases is the letter form of report not used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When reader is a close associate",
            "b) When subject matter is brief",
            "c) When there is breakdown of machinery",
            "d) When subject matter pertains to a few topics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A feasibility report is written before starting a new project. It is done to give an overview of the targets that the project hopes to meet, and addresses how effectively these targets can be met. This type of report is valid both for government and private organizations."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Where is the signature mentioned in a memorandum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top left",
            "b) Top right",
            "c) Bottom left",
            "d) Bottom right"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trouble report includes breakdown of machinery, accidents, deaths, fires, etc. It lists down precautions to be taken in future in order to prevent a reoccurrence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Which of these is usually written in a form of a memorandum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informal reports",
            "b) Formal reports",
            "c) Professional reports",
            "d) Business reports"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A written report is more formal in nature than an oral report and it removes almost every flaw inherent in an oral report. "
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a formal report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informational",
            "b) Informal",
            "c) Interpretative",
            "d) Routine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Written reports can be of two types. They are: formal reports and informal reports. Informal reports are normally written in the form of a memorandum or a letter."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Into which of these types are formal reports not classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informational",
            "b) Interpretative",
            "c) Oral",
            "d) Routine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Formal reports can be classified into three different types. They are : informational, interpretative and routine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Which of these reports provide information without any evaluation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informational",
            "b) Interpretative",
            "c) Routine",
            "d) Progress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Formal reports are written reports. They can be classified into three types : informational, interpretative and routine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "_______ report provides rational findings.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informative",
            "b) Interpretative",
            "c) Routine",
            "d) Progress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Informational reports accumulate and provide information without any assessment or evaluation. They do not make any recommendations they do not give any findings."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Interpretative reports are also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) recommendation reports",
            "b) routine reports",
            "c) progress reports",
            "d) informal reports"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Interpretative reports do not merely provide data. They assess this data and provide rational findings and worthwhile recommendations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Which of these reports are written for recording information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Informational",
            "b) Interpretative",
            "c) Routine",
            "d) Recommendation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Interpretative reports are also known as recommendation reports. They assess the data and provide rational findings and worthwhile recommendations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of these is not mentioned in a progress report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Name of project",
            "b) Right choice of instruments",
            "c) Nature of work",
            "d) Amount of work left"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Routine reports are normally written for recording information which is required at periodic intervals.  In most cases there may be printed forms where relevant gaps have to be filled with acquired data."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Which of these reports involves the checking of a piece of equipment to see if it’s still in working condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progress report",
            "b) Laboratory report",
            "c) Inspection report",
            "d) Inventory report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A progress report should contain information like: Name of project, nature of project, extent of work to be completed, amount of work left, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "A technical report establishes a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) illogical conclusion",
            "b) logical conclusion",
            "c) personal prejudice",
            "d) misplaced learning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A technical report reduces to writing the facts of a particular situation, project, process or test. "
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Which of these must never be a basis for a technical report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Facts",
            "b) Tests",
            "c) Personal prejudices",
            "d) Experiments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A technical report establishes a logical conclusion on the basis of the facts laid down and the purpose for which these facts are required. "
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided in a technical report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Facts",
            "b) Logical conclusion",
            "c) Objective evaluation",
            "d) Subjective evaluation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A report must never be based on personal prejudices and misplaced learning. It must be objective. It highlights the significance of the facts."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a parameter in a report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extent of information",
            "b) Quality of information",
            "c) Age of writer",
            "d) Ability to acquire information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A technical report must always be objective. There is very little place for subjective evaluation in a report. A technical report establishes a logical conclusion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a parameter of a report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ability to acquire additional information",
            "b) Quality of additional information acquired",
            "c) Ability to arrive at subjective evaluation",
            "d) Ability to provide worthwhile recommendations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A report may be used for reading or hearing. The language would change in both cases because spoken language is different from written language. "
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "To which of these people is the report not very crucial?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engineers",
            "b) Scientists",
            "c) Teachers",
            "d) Business executives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are eight basic parameters in a report: extent and quality of information, ability to acquire additional information, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of these reports is raised annually?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inventory reports",
            "b) Confidential reports",
            "c) Laboratory reports",
            "d) Inspection reports"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are many basic parameters of a report: Ability to acquire additional information, quality of additional information acquired, ability to arrive at objective evaluation, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of a report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Front matter",
            "b) Gender",
            "c) Front cover",
            "d) Title page"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reports are of crucial importance to engineers, scientists, business executives and public administrators. "
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of these is written like a business letter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introductory letter",
            "b) Covering letter",
            "c) Informal letter",
            "d) Personal letter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Forwarding letter can be of two types. They are: Covering letter and introductory letter. Both of them are meant for the primary recipient of the report."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Introductory letter serves the purpose of a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) summary",
            "b) preface",
            "c) main part",
            "d) conclusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Covering letter: This type of letter is only a record of transmission of the report."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Where is introductory letter placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At the beginning",
            "b) At the end",
            "c) After the title page",
            "d) Just before the last page"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is: Introductory letter serves the purpose of a preface or introduction. It is written like any other business letter."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of these introduces the report to the reader?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acknowledgement",
            "b) Preface",
            "c) Summary",
            "d) Abstract"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An introductory letter aims to introduce the scope and purpose of the report. It must be placed immediately after the title page; which means that it must be bound with the report."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Which of these tells us what the report is about?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abstract",
            "b) Summary",
            "c) Acknowledgements",
            "d) Table of contents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A preface is anything said or written by way of introduction or preliminary explanation. Thus a preface to a report introduces the report to the reader."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "______ gives the substance of the report.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abstract",
            "b) Summary",
            "c) Preface",
            "d) Table of contents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A distinction must be made between an abstract and a summary. An abstract tells us in brief what the report is about. "
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "An abstract is _____ of the original report.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-5 percent",
            "b) 5-10 percent",
            "c) 6-12 percent",
            "d) 7-13 percent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is: Summary gives the substance of the report. An abstract only gives the matter covered in the report."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "A summary is _____ of the original report.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-5 percent",
            "b) 5-10 percent",
            "c) 12-15 percent",
            "d) 15-20 percent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: An abstract is 2-5 percent of the original report. An abstract tells us in brief what the report is about. "
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of the main body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introduction",
            "b) Conclusion",
            "c) Complaint",
            "d) Recommendation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A summary is 5-10 percent of the original report. A summary becomes crucial when the report is long and gives the substance of the report. "
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which aspect of a product is a customer not required to know?",
        "Options": [
            "a) About the product",
            "b) Age of seller",
            "c) Advantages of the product",
            "d) Value for money"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Customers need to know three points about a product. They are: about the product, advantages of the product over other similar products and the value for money that the product provides. "
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of an advertisement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inspire a customer",
            "b) Arouse a desire",
            "c) Discourage the buyer",
            "d) Convince the buyer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any advertisement has these four characteristics : An advertisement must inspire a customer, must arouse a desire, must convince the buyer about the quality and it must motivate the customer to actually go and buy the product."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of these media is not used for advertisement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Newspapers",
            "b) Magazines",
            "c) Billboards",
            "d) Notebooks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Seven types of media are used for advertisement. They are: newspapers, magazines, billboards, direct mail, radio, TV and cinema and Internet. "
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Which of these is cheap and informative?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Television",
            "b) Newspapers",
            "c) Magazine",
            "d) Cinema"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The choice of medium of advertisement depends on the contents of the message, customer whom the advertisement wishes to attract and the money available for the advertisement."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Which of these contain no illustrations or logos?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TV",
            "b) Magazine",
            "c) Classified advertisements",
            "d) Cinema"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Basic principles of advertisement remains the same for different mediums. An advertisement in a newspaper would be different from that in a magazine."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "When a newspaper advertisement looks like a new story, it is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) classified notice",
            "b) reading notice",
            "c) writing notice",
            "d) spoken notice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A newspaper is an intellectual way of reporting events and providing information. It is a cheap device and reach is huge."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Which of these media needs a script for an advertisement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Newspaper advertisements",
            "b) Classified advertisements",
            "c) Radio",
            "d) Magazine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Classified advertisements are small and one column wide. These advertisements contain no illustrations or logos."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which of these is the best medium for advertisement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Television",
            "b) Newspapers",
            "c) Magazines",
            "d) Radio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is: When a newspaper advertisement looks like a new story, it is called reading notice. They are the most expensive kind of newspaper advertisement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Which of these cannot be a billboard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wall",
            "b) Static panel",
            "c) Banner",
            "d) Paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A billboard could be a wall, a static panel or a banner. It is essentially an outdoor form of advertisement. In case of billboards, consumers come to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Graphic techniques help to understand ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) business reports",
            "b) friendly letters",
            "c) notices",
            "d) classified advertisements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Graphic techniques help to understand business reports. Graphic techniques include headings, tables, charts, graphs, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Which of these can be dependent or independent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tables",
            "b) Graphs",
            "c) Figures",
            "d) Charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Graphic aids provide large data in a short place. It helps to communicate better.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Which of these does a figure not include?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graphs",
            "b) Tables",
            "c) Charts",
            "d) Drawings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Graphic aids are of two types. They are: tables and figures. Tables can be dependent or independent. "
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "What is the first column of a table called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Head",
            "b) Subhead",
            "c) Heading",
            "d) Boxhead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Graphic aids are of two types. They are: tables and figures. Tables can be dependent or independent. Figures include graphs, charts, drawings, photos and maps."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Which of these is used to give additional information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subhead",
            "b) Boxhead",
            "c) Footnote",
            "d) Dash"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. An independent table is complete in itself. It is placed separately from the text. It must be given a number and a title. "
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Which of the following shows a trend of progress over a known period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectilinear graph",
            "b) Tables",
            "c) Multiline graphs",
            "d) Bar graphs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A table has rows which run horizontally and columns which run vertically. Its first column is called subhead. "
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Which of these presents data of related units?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectilinear graph",
            "b) Tables",
            "c) Multiline graphs",
            "d) Bar graphs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A dash shows that no data exists for that column. A footnote may be used to give additional information while preparing a table."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "The Chambers Everyday Dictionary describes precis as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) a summary",
            "b) a presentation",
            "c) a story",
            "d) an incident"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Precis writing is the art of presenting certain information in a condensed form. "
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "A precis must use the ______ tense of verbs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) present",
            "b) past",
            "c) future",
            "d) present continuous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: The Chambers Everyday Dictionary describes precis as an abstract or a summary. "
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "A precis must always have a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) subheading",
            "b) heading",
            "c) story",
            "d) incident"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The biggest advantage of a precis, however, is that it saves time. Most modern executives are constantly working against time."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "A precis must be how long?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One-third of original passage",
            "b) Two-third of original passage",
            "c) Same as of original passage",
            "d) One-fifth of original passage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A precis must use the past tense of verbs. A precis of crucial importance. It enables a person to compress large information without losing anything worthwhile."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Which of these are not allowed in a precis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semicolon",
            "b) Verbs",
            "c) Heading",
            "d) Abbreviations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A precis must always have a heading. The title must be the shortest possible and it must reflect the central idea of the passage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "In a precis, conjunctions can be replaced by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full stop",
            "b) Semicolon",
            "c) Apostrophe",
            "d) Dash"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A precis must be one-third the length of the original passage. It may sometimes be less than one-third if the original passage has indulged in too much circumlocution. "
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Which of these is called a percentage graph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bar graph",
            "b) Table",
            "c) Pie graph",
            "d) Precis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abbreviations are not allowed in a precis nor can the parameters of grammar be compromised. Adverbs and adjectives can be eliminated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Which of these contains symbols?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pie graph",
            "b) Pictorial graph",
            "c) Precis",
            "d) Bar graph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: In a precis, conjunctions can be replaced by semicolon.  Adverbs and adjectives can be eliminated in order to reduce the length of the passage."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of precis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Precis of speech",
            "b) Precis of correspondence",
            "c) Tables",
            "d) Telegraphese"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Precis can be of four types. They are: precis of speech, precis of continuous matter, precis of correspondence and telegraphese."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Which of the following is NOT a rule of precis writing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Always have a heading",
            "b) Use as extensive vocabulary as possible",
            "c) Remove any irrelevant information present in the original passage",
            "d) Do not use any short forms or abbreviations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The objective of a precis is to summarize a longer, wordier piece of writing. So, it should be short and crisp, such that the crux of the original passage is adequately conveyed in as less words as possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a precis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Imagery",
            "b) Verbs",
            "c) Pronouns",
            "d) Indirect speech"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A precis should be written in third person and in the past tense. All pronouns must be in third person. "
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "_______ in a speech must be avoided in a summary.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Facts",
            "b) Ideas",
            "c) Repetitions",
            "d) Verbs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Figurative language and imagery should not be used. Language which is needlessly poetic should be avoided at all costs."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Which of these is not included in precis of continuous matter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parliamentary reports",
            "b) Correspondence",
            "c) Reports of evidence",
            "d) Articles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Repetitions in a speech must be avoided in a summary. Ideas which have similar meanings must be clubbed together and produced as one central idea."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Which of these is also known as abstract?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Index precis",
            "b) Narrative precis",
            "c) Precis of speech",
            "d) Telegraphese"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Continuous matter includes every kind of matter other than correspondence. It includes question and answer form (parliamentary reports, reports of evidence, etc.) or articles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Index precis is also known as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) docket",
            "b) telegraphese",
            "c) narrative precis",
            "d) precis of speech"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. The date and time of the passage must be given in precis of continuous matter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "How must the date be written in an index precis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) November 15, 2004",
            "b) 15 November, 2004",
            "c) 2004, November 15",
            "d) November 2004, 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Precis of correspondence may be of two types. They are: Index- precis and narrative- precis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of a good essay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brevity",
            "b) Dignified style",
            "c) Fakeness",
            "d) Personal touch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. An essay could be short or long. It could give personal opinions or information on a subject. "
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in a good essay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slang",
            "b) Dignified words",
            "c) Brevity",
            "d) Unity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A good essay must have five characteristics. They are: unity, order in line of thought, Brevity, dignified and literary style and the personal touch."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of essay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrative essay",
            "b) Descriptive essay",
            "c) Argumentative essay",
            "d) Personal essay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A good essay must have a dignified and literary style. It cannot have slang, colloquial terms and free constructions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Which of these essays tells a story?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrative essays",
            "b) Descriptive essays",
            "c) Reflective essays",
            "d) Argumentative essays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Essays are of five types. They are: Narrative essays, descriptive essays, argumentative essays, reflective essays and expository essays. "
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "In which of these essays, the writer arrives at a conclusion by logical reasoning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrative essays",
            "b) Descriptive essays",
            "c) Reflective essays",
            "d) Argumentative essays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Narrative essays narrate a story or an event. The story or event could be real or imaginary, like an accident, a festival and so on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "________ essays are a collection of one’s thoughts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrative",
            "b) Expository",
            "c) Argumentative",
            "d) Reflective"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Descriptive essays describe a place, person or a thing which may be real or imaginary. "
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Which of these explains a subject?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrative essays",
            "b) Expository essays",
            "c) Argumentative essays",
            "d) Reflective essays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Argumentative essays are argumentative in nature. The writer arrives at a conclusion by logical reasoning."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Which kind of essay uses the five senses (touch, smell, taste, sound, sight) to enhance the imagery of the setting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrative essays",
            "b) Descriptive  essays",
            "c) Expository essays",
            "d) Argumentative  essays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Reflective essays consist of reflection of thoughts on topics of abstract nature. These include habits, qualities, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Interviews are conversations with  _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) fun",
            "b) purpose",
            "c) friendliness",
            "d) informality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Interviews are conversations with purpose. For the employer the purpose is to determine the most suitable person for the job."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of interview?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Screening interview",
            "b) Stress interview",
            "c) Music interview",
            "d) Lunch interview"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Interview is a formal face-to-face meeting. A job interview is a formal meeting between a job seeker and an employer. "
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Which kind of interview includes a process in which the employability of the job applicant is evaluated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stress interview",
            "b) Screening interview",
            "c) Group interview",
            "d) Behavioural interview"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. All job interviews have the same objective, but employers reach that objective in a variety of ways. "
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "How many styles are used in a screening interview?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Five",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Interviews can be of nine types: They are Screening interview, stress interview, behavioural interview, the audition, group interview, telephone, lunch interview, video interview and sequential interview."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "In which of these interviews, insults are common?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Screening interview",
            "b) Stress interview",
            "c) Behavioural interview",
            "d) Group interview"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the screening interview, companies use screening tools to ensure that candidates meet minimum qualification requirements. "
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Which of these interviews is adapted for computer programmers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stress interview",
            "b) The group interview",
            "c) The screening interview",
            "d) The audition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two styles used in a screening interview. They are: the directive style and the meandering style. "
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "In which of these, more than one candidate is interviewed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The behavioural interview",
            "b) The stress interview",
            "c) The group interview",
            "d) The audition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In stress interview, insults and miscommunication is common. All this is designed to see whether you have the mettle to withstand the company culture or other potential stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Which of these interviews is taken for a candidate far away?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lunch interview",
            "b) Telephone",
            "c) Stress interview",
            "d) Group interview"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For some positions such as computer programmers or trainers, companies want to see you in action before they make their decision. Here, the audition type is adapted. "
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "A job interview is usually how long?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 minutes",
            "b) 60 minutes",
            "c) 90 minutes",
            "d) 100 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A job interview is usually 30 minutes long. In this time, the candidate must establish a relationship with the interviewer, impress and convince him."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a step in the preparation of an interview?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analyzing yourself",
            "b) Identifying your skills",
            "c) Being negative",
            "d) Revising your subject"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are five steps in the preparation of an interview. They are: analyzing yourself, identifying your skills, researching the job position, revising your subject knowledge and developing your interview file."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "In the preparation of an interview, which step is to research your job position?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Second",
            "b) Third",
            "c) Fourth",
            "d) First"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the preparation of an interview, researching your job position in the third step. The first step is to analyze yourself followed by identifying your skills. "
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a step in self – analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analyzing background",
            "b) Identifying accomplishments",
            "c) Identifying achievements",
            "d) Complaining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Developing the interview file is the last step in the preparation of an interview preceded by revising your subject knowledge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Which of these is the third aspect of self analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Identifying achievements",
            "b) Identifying special interests",
            "c) Analyzing career goals",
            "d) Identifying accomplishments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Self- analysis is the first step in planning for any interview. We cannot project ourselves successfully unless we know our strengths and weaknesses properly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "______ skills are assessed in an interview.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Listening",
            "b) Blabbering",
            "c) Singing",
            "d) Dancing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Self- analysis includes five steps for efficiency preparation. They are: analyzing our background, identifying accomplishments, achievements, special interests and hobbies and analyzing career goals. Complaining will in no way enable us to evaluate our merits and shortcomings. "
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Which of these documents need not be in your interview file?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interview letter",
            "b) Original degrees",
            "c) Family photo",
            "d) Certificates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The third aspect of self analysis is identifying special interests and hobbies. A list of such activities should be made."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of these ways can’t be used to research about the company?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Visiting website",
            "b) Refer books",
            "c) School books",
            "d) Refer annual report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are two types of skills that might be assessed during an interview. They are: listening and skills and intuitive skills."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of interview question?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open",
            "b) Closed",
            "c) Probing",
            "d) Musical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are seven different types of interview questions. They are: open, closed, probing, reflective, loaded, hypothetical and leading questions."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of these questions asks the candidate to talk about something?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open questions",
            "b) Closed questions",
            "c) Probing questions",
            "d) Loaded questions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An open question asks the candidate to talk about something. Its main purpose is to encourage the candidates to talk broadly about a topic or subject. "
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Which of these is an open question?",
        "Options": [
            "a) What are the advantages of a mixed economy?",
            "b) When did you complete your graduation?",
            "c) Do you know data processing?",
            "d) What was your major subject in college?"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An open question asks the candidate to talk about something. Its main purpose is to encourage the candidates to talk broadly about a topic or subject. For example: What are the advantages of a mixed economy? "
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Which of these questions expect specific information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open questions",
            "b) Closed questions",
            "c) Probing questions",
            "d) Reflective questions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike open questions, closed questions limit the scope of the response by asking the candidates to provide specific information or facts."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of these questions are asked for confirmation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open questions",
            "b) Closed questions",
            "c) Reflective questions",
            "d) Probing questions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Probing questions encourage the candidate to talk in greater depth about a topic or subject."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "______ questions assess the candidate’s response to a sensitive issue.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closed",
            "b) Probing",
            "c) Loaded",
            "d) Leading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reflective questions are asked to confirm the statements given by the candidate. The purpose is to check that the interviewer understands what the candidate has said."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an answering strategy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accuracy",
            "b) Focus",
            "c) Illogical thinking",
            "d) Brevity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Loaded questions assess the candidate’s response to a sensitive issue, subject or point. "
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in an interview?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attentiveness",
            "b) Accuracy",
            "c) Negative attitudes",
            "d) Clarity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A leading question is asked to obtain a desired response. It leads the candidate to a particular answer."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in an interview?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clarity",
            "b) Smile",
            "c) Confusion",
            "d) Confidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The interviewee should speak clearly and effectively. He/she should not be confused while he/she speaks and instead should speak confidently and with a smile. "
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of a group personality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spirit of conformity",
            "b) Respect for group values",
            "c) Collective power",
            "d) Disrespect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A group personality must have five characteristics. They are: spirit of conformity, respect for group values, respect to change, group prejudice and collective power."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "The word discuss is derived from _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) discutere",
            "b) discuter",
            "c) discutera",
            "d) discutare"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The word discuss is derived from the latin word discutere that means to shake or strike. The word discussion is a noun. "
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an ingredient of a discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purpose",
            "b) Planning",
            "c) Rudeness",
            "d) Leadership"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A discussion has five ingredients. They are: purpose, planning, participation, informality and leadership. "
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Which of these is the first ingredient in a group discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planning",
            "b) Purpose",
            "c) Informality",
            "d) Leadership"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first ingredient of an effective discussion is purpose. Unless there is a clear purpose there will not be any discussion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Planning is the _______ ingredient of discussion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) first",
            "b) second",
            "c) third",
            "d) fifth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Planning is the second ingredient of discussion. We can’t rely on any random or on the sop expression of feelings or ideas."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Which of these is the fourth ingredient in a group discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Participation",
            "b) Informality",
            "c) Leadership",
            "d) Planning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Participation is the third ingredient of a group discussion. Participation is the very life of a meaningful discussion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Which of these is the final ingredient in a group discussion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purpose",
            "b) Planning",
            "c) Participation",
            "d) Leadership"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Informality is the fourth ingredient in a group discussion. Informality and cordiality are essential to encourage the fullest possible participation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an information based system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MIS",
            "b) DSS",
            "c) SIS",
            "d) SDS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In today’s dynamic environment, information is the lifeblood of business. Information based systems such as MIS, DSS and SIS all rest on the communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Which of these factors is not required for communication growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Growth in size of organisations",
            "b) Negative atmosphere",
            "c) Globalisation",
            "d) Public relations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Communication growth requires eight factors. They are: growth in size of organisations, globalization, growth of trade unions, public relations, and so on. A negative atmosphere isn’t conducive to communication growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Globalization, growth of trade unions, public relations and a positive atmosphere are some of the factors that enable ____________.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good friendships",
            "b) Happiness",
            "c) Isolation from society",
            "d) Communication growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Communication growth requires eight factors. They are: growth in size of organisations, globalization, growth of trade unions, public relations, and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which of these does not come under behavioural sciences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Globalization",
            "b) Psychology",
            "c) Sociology",
            "d) Transactional Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Every organization has a social responsibility, specially towards the customers, government, suppliers and the public at large. "
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Which of these element is not involved in the process of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pipe",
            "b) Sender",
            "c) Message",
            "d) Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Modern management is deeply influenced by exciting discoveries made in behavioural sciences like Psychology, Sociology, Transactional Analysis, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Which of these is the third element of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sender",
            "b) Channel",
            "c) Message",
            "d) Receiver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are four elements in the process of communication. They are: sender, message , channel, receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "For effective communication, which of these commandments should one not follow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Objective of communication",
            "b) Inadequate medium",
            "c) Clarity",
            "d) Adequate medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A sender is the person who transmits a message. A message could be verbal or non- verbal as appearance, body language, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "To make our communication effective, we should follow _____ C’s and _____ S’s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) seven, four",
            "b) seven, three",
            "c) six, four",
            "d) six, three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Channel is the third element in the process of communication. A message may be sent via an electronic word processing system or through the printed work or other media."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Which of these does not come under the four S’s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplicity",
            "b) Strength",
            "c) Sincerity",
            "d) Shock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order to ensure effective communication, one must take care of the ten commandments. They are: objective of communication, clarity in the use of language, adequate medium, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Which of these is the external sounds present in the channels of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noise",
            "b) Semantic problems",
            "c) Cultural barriers",
            "d) Over communication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Noise is the external sounds present in the channels of communication, which results in the reduction of the audibility or omission of some words from the message."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Which of these should not be avoided for effective communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noise",
            "b) Planning",
            "c) Semantic problems",
            "d) Wrong assumptions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lack of planning must be avoided for effects communication. There are innumerable examples of people who would give an ill planned, long winding lecture while a short presentation with tables or graphs would be sufficient. "
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "__________ are problems arising from expression.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cultural barriers",
            "b) Semantic problems",
            "c) Wrong assumptions",
            "d) Selecting perception"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Semantic problems are problems arising from expression or transmission of meaning in communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "In which of these problems, is the actual message lost in the abundance of transmitted information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selecting perception",
            "b) Over communication",
            "c) Under communication",
            "d) Filtering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Both encoding and decoding of message are influenced by our emotions. Emotions play a very important role in our lives. "
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "_______ means to impart understanding of the message.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Encoding",
            "b) Receiver",
            "c) Decoding",
            "d) Feedback"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of over communication, the actual message is lost in the jungle of information whereas in under communication the sender is blamed for sharing less information. "
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "When is the communication process complete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the sender transmits the message",
            "b) When the message enters the channel",
            "c) When the message leaves the channel",
            "d) When the receiver understands the message."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Communication should serve as a conflict- reduction exercise. When people start competing for the fulfillment of their narrow interests communication suffers."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "______ is the first enemy of communication.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noise",
            "b) Clarity",
            "c) Politeness",
            "d) Completeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Decoding means to impart understanding of the message. Receiver has to identify the person, words symbols, etc.."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Which of these must be avoided for effective communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sharing of activity",
            "b) Listening",
            "c) Ambiguity",
            "d) Politeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Communication is complete only when the receiver understands the message. Many communication problems arise because of misunderstandings."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a commandment of effective communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clarity in language",
            "b) Listen poorly",
            "c) Home communication skills",
            "d) Adequate medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Noise is the first and foremost enemy of communication. Every possible effort must be made to eliminate the element of noise that distorts communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "On the basis of mutual participation, communication is of how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On the basis of mutual participation of the sender and receiver,  communication is of two types. They are: one-way communication and two-way communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "In an organization, which of these is not a type of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Downward",
            "b) Upward",
            "c) Curve",
            "d) Horizontal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. On the basis of nature, communicating can be of two types. They are: formal and informal communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "_______ communication is a dictator type communication.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two-way",
            "b) Three- way",
            "c) Four- way",
            "d) One- way"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In pyramidal hierarchy system in the organization communication can be identified as: downward, upward, horizontal and diagonal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "Any business house is concerned with _______ communication.",
        "Options": [
            "a) external",
            "b) dumb",
            "c) deaf",
            "d) blind"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Two-way communication is the most democratic way of communication. One-way communication is a dictator type communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "_______ communication flows from a superior to a subordinate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upward",
            "b) Downward",
            "c) Diagonal",
            "d) Lateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statement is: One-way communication is a dictator type communication where ordering or instructing takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a limitations of downward communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Under communication",
            "b) Over communication",
            "c) Car communication",
            "d) Distortion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Any business house is concerned with two types of communication. They are: external communication and internal communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of these moves from the grass root level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Downward communication",
            "b) Diagonal communication",
            "c) Upward communication",
            "d) Lateral communication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Downward communication flows from a superior to a subordinate. Orders, instructions, job-sheets, etc. fall under downward communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a method for upward communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open-door policy",
            "b) Complaints",
            "c) Suggestion boxes",
            "d) Scolding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Downward communication has five major limitations. They are: under and over communication, delay, loss of information, distortion and built-in resistance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most frequently used channel of communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal communication",
            "b) Diagonal communication",
            "c) Downward communication",
            "d) Upward communication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Upward communication moves from the grass root level to the higher levels in an organization. Its main objectives are: providing feedback, constructive suggestions, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of these is a type of informal communication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reports",
            "b) Orders",
            "c) Instructions",
            "d) Grapevine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There exists in every organization an informal channel, often called the grapevine, that does not arise out of the organizational needs but is an integral part of the communication system."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of grapevine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gossip",
            "b) Probability",
            "c) Rope",
            "d) Cluster"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Rumors that are all time spreading in any organization follow the grapevine. It follows no setlines, nor any definite rules, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of grapevine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double strand",
            "b) Single strand",
            "c) Gossip",
            "d) Cluster"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grapevine is classified into four types. They are: single strand, gossip, probability and cluster. "
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": " Which of these involves the passing of information through a long line of people?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cluster",
            "b) Single strand",
            "c) Gossip",
            "d) Probability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grapevine is classified into four types. They are: single strand, gossip, probability and cluster. There is no such type as double strand. "
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Which of these grapevine chains is random?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single strand",
            "b) Cluster",
            "c) Probability",
            "d) Gossip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The single strand involves the passing of information through a long line of people to the ultimate recipient. "
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most common type of grapevine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gossip chain",
            "b) Single strand chain",
            "c) Probability chain",
            "d) Cluster chain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The probability chain is a random process in which one transmits the information to others in accordance with the laws of probability and it goes on."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a limitation of grapevine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distortion",
            "b) Slow process",
            "c) Incomplete information",
            "d) Damaging swiftness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the cluster chain, one tells selected people who may in turn relay the information to other selected individuals. This the most common type of informal communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of effective listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discriminative listening",
            "b) Evaluative listening",
            "c) Irritated listening",
            "d) Appreciative listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. The grapevine provides feedback to the management. It enables them to know what the subordinates think about the organization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided for effective listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Patience",
            "b) Politeness",
            "c) Talking",
            "d) Attentiveness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The grapevine has three major limitations: distortion, incomplete information and damaging swiftness. A grapevine spreads baseless or distorted news and the information is usually incomplete. The swiftness with which the grapevine transmits may even be damaging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided for an effective speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determination of the purpose",
            "b) Selection of message",
            "c) Lack of interest",
            "d) Selection of theme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Public speaking means addressing a group or a large gathering of people. It is issuing instructions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Which of these factors is not required to determine the purpose of speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing information",
            "b) Discouragement",
            "c) Accepting ideas",
            "d) Entertainment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Public speaking is not only a verbal activity, it includes non- verbal means also. "
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Which of these ingredients is not required for selection of theme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planning",
            "b) Disorganisation",
            "c) Preparation",
            "d) Organisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Four principles must be followed for an effective speech. They are: analysis of audience and occasion, determine the purpose, selection of message or theme and speech delivery. "
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided for an effective speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planning of speech",
            "b) Preparation of speech",
            "c) Long sentences",
            "d) Organisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three main factors are required to determination the purpose of speech. They are: providing information, to make acceptance of ideas and entertainment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided during the delivery of a speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Confidence",
            "b) Clarity",
            "c) Pauses",
            "d) Rudeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three main ingredients are required for selection of message or theme. They are: planning, preparation and organisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of public speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short speech",
            "b) Informal speech",
            "c) Written speech",
            "d) Professional speech"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is worthwhile to prepare the matter carefully. Use short sentences. Information should be conveyed in least possible words without leaving out anything important. "
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "What is the maximum time for a short speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ten minutes",
            "b) Thirty minutes",
            "c) Forty- five minutes",
            "d) One hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Presentation or speech should be delivered with confidence. Delivery must be with clarity and precision. A good speaker always pauses on punctuation marks."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Which of these does not come under short speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introducing dignitaries",
            "b) Presenting reports",
            "c) Giving a briefing",
            "d) Presenting an award"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Public speeches can be of four types. They are: short speech, long speech, informal speech and professional speech. "
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of means of speech delivery?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reading",
            "b) Memorization",
            "c) Scolding",
            "d) Impromptu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A short speech is short in length and ranges from one to ten minutes. A long speech varies from ten minutes to one hour."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an ingredient of the speech process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Message",
            "b) Audience",
            "c) Feedback",
            "d) Reading comprehension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Speaking is an important mode of expression which is used frequently. We speak more than we write. "
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in the message of a speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clarity",
            "b) Confusion",
            "c) Voice Modulation",
            "d) Politeness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Speaking is a combination of verbal and non-verbal means. People listen to those who impress them, who impart knowledge, who give something new, who relate things and ideas."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Which of these is the most important element of the speech process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Message",
            "b) Audience",
            "c) Feedback",
            "d) Speech style"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A speech process has five ingredients. They are: message, audience, speech style, feedback and conversation and oral skills."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "Which of these factors need not be considered while preparing speech for the audience?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of people",
            "b) Age of audience",
            "c) Appearance of audience",
            "d) Nature of purpose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Confusing words should be avoided while speaking. Such words will hamper the clarity in communicating the message. A good speech is one that is delivered with a clear tone, and one that isn’t too loud and jarring to hear. The speaker should be calm and polite, and exercise proper voice modulation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of these factors distinguish one speaker from the other speakers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Audience",
            "b) Message",
            "c) Speech style",
            "d) Feedback"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Audience is the most important element of the speech process. Speech is meant for the audience and play a great role in determining the material to be used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Which of these is used as a basis for improvement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speech style",
            "b) Feedback",
            "c) Oral skills",
            "d) Conversation skills"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Many factors should be considered while preparing speech for the audience, like: nature of purpose, number of people, age and sex of audience, educational qualification of audience, interest and expectation from speaker, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Which of these factors is not used for feedback by an audience that is listening to a speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pronunciation",
            "b) Content",
            "c) Hairstyle",
            "d) Speech delivery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Speech style distinguishes a speaker from the other speakers. Style is a pattern of speaking adopted by a speaker. "
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Which of these factors do not make the oral discourse effective?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dullness",
            "b) Fluency",
            "c) Self expression",
            "d) Phonetics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Feedback means the responses from the audience to the speech. The feedback is used as a basis for improvement."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided while speaking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluency",
            "b) Jargon",
            "c) Clear voice",
            "d) Abstract words"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Seven factors are used for feedback by audience. They are: pronunciation, speech delivery, content, audience awareness, body language, use of audio visual aids and quality of interaction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Which of these is the study and classification of speech sounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gestures",
            "b) Speech style",
            "c) Phonetics",
            "d) Spoof"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Body language can make or break a speech. Audience receives as much information from our body as from words."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an element of the speaking technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voice quality",
            "b) Word stress",
            "c) Appearance",
            "d) Correct tones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phonetics is the study and classification of speech sounds. Knowledge of phonetics helps in correct pronunciation of English language. "
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of these means giving emphasis to a syllable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voice quality",
            "b) Word stress",
            "c) Tone",
            "d) Message"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Speaking technique has four main elements. They are: word stress, voice quality, correct tones and types of tones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of these factors is not involved in the determination of correct tone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch",
            "b) Dressing style",
            "c) Quality",
            "d) Strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Word stress means giving emphasis to a word or a syllable when pronouncing while speaking. Speaker presents facts, ideas through his speech."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of tone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urgent tone",
            "b) Serious tone",
            "c) Restrained tone",
            "d) Jumping tone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three factors are involved in the determination of correct tone. They are: pitch, quality and strength. "
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Which of these tones represent thoughtfulness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serious tone",
            "b) Urgent  tone",
            "c) Happy tone",
            "d) Outraged tone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are seven types of tones. They are : serious tone, urgent tone, restrained tone, outraged tone, humorous tone, reflective tone and happy tone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Which of these tones is an unemotional tone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Happy tone",
            "b) Outraged tone",
            "c) Restrained tone",
            "d) Humorous tone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A serious tone expresses careful consideration, solemn or thoughtfulness. It exhibits that the speaker is sincere and earnestly putting his point of view. "
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "______ tone is used when speaker wants to bring about a good impression of her life.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Outraged",
            "b) Reflective",
            "c) Restrained",
            "d) Urgent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Restrained tone is reserved as an unemotional tone. It is subtle and not orante. It is prohibitive in character. It favours self control. "
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which of these tones is used to express contentment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serious tone",
            "b) Happy tone",
            "c) Outraged tone",
            "d) Urgent tone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Reflective tone is used when speaker wants to bring about a good impression of her life."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a step in the listening process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To stop talking",
            "b) Receiving",
            "c) Misinterpreting",
            "d) Responding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Listening means to give one’s attention to what others say. It also means to respond to advice or request."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Which of these is the first step in the listening process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stop talking",
            "b) Receiving",
            "c) Interpreting",
            "d) Responding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Listening consists of four main steps. They are: To stop talking, receiving, interpreting and responding. Hearing is different from listening. "
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Which of these is the third step in the listening process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stop talking",
            "b) Interpreting",
            "c) Responding",
            "d) Receiving"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Being a good speaker isn’t everything. Being a good listener is also important. For that, one has to know when to stop talking. Not only is it respectful towards the speaker, it also enables the listener to gather more from the speech. One must keep quiet when speaker has begun his speech."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "_______ is the last step of the listening process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receiving",
            "b) Interpreting",
            "c) Responding",
            "d) Stop talking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Interpreting is the third step in the listening process. After listening to the talk seriously and noting important points, interpret the contents of the speech."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Appreciative listening",
            "b) Superficial listening",
            "c) Focused listening",
            "d) Musical listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct statement is: Responding is the last step of the listening process. One way to respond is to ask questions to the speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which of these types of listening lacks depth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Appreciative listening",
            "b) Superficial listening",
            "c) Focused listening",
            "d) Evaluative listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Hearing means perceiving with ears. It is the effort to decipher the phonetic sound from the speaker. It is a physical act."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "In which of these types of listening, does the listener feel grateful?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superficial listening",
            "b) Attentive listening",
            "c) Appreciative listening",
            "d) Evaluative listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Listening can be of six types. They are: superficial listening, appreciative listening, focused listening, evaluative listening, attentive listening and empathetic listening."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which of these types of listening is followed by skilled listeners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Focused listening",
            "b) Evaluative listening",
            "c) Attentive listening",
            "d) Empathetic listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Superficial listening is apparent listening lacking depth or understanding. It is not thorough listening, it is cursory listening. "
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "In which of these, the listener puts himself in place of the speaker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Focused listening",
            "b) Evaluative listening",
            "c) Attentive listening",
            "d) Empathetic listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the listener expresses gratitude or pleasure for the speech, it is called appreciative listening. Listeners applaud the speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided for effective listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-listening analysis",
            "b) Listening to structured talks",
            "c) Team listening",
            "d) Predicting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. A successful manager or businessman should be a trained listener. He/she should adopt certain strategies for success."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "In which of these does the listener pick up special features of the speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Listening in conversational interaction",
            "b) Listening to structured talks",
            "c) Predicting",
            "d) Team listening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: One should follow seven strategies for effective listening. They are: listening in conversational interaction, listening to structured talks, pre-listening analysis, not predicting, links between parts of the speech, team listening and listening and note taking."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "A well organised talk is a _______ talk.",
        "Options": [
            "a) short",
            "b) long",
            "c) random",
            "d) structured"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Listening in conversational interaction is an important listening strategy. One has to listen to the conversation and pick up the special features of the speaker’s presentation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided in pre-listening analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mental discipline",
            "b) Concentration",
            "c) Prejudices",
            "d) Patience"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct statement is: A well organised talk is a structured talk. It is an effectively prepared talk for a special purpose. "
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "In which of these, should the listener be able to make connections between different segments of the speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Listening to structured talks",
            "b) Links between parts of the speech",
            "c) Team listening",
            "d) Predicting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For pre-listening analysis, exercise mental discipline and concentrate seriously. Avoid prejudices against the speaker."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Which of these is based of effective listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Note taking",
            "b) Notice writing",
            "c) Letter writing",
            "d) Predicting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement is true. Predicting is the technique to forecast what the speaker will say or place the idea before the audience. "
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Which of these should be avoided while note taking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration",
            "b) Evaluation",
            "c) Listening",
            "d) Using phrases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A good listener must be able to establish relation between different parts of the speech. This is possible if listener is attentive and keeps his mind open."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a type of text for reading?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reference material",
            "b) Chats",
            "c) Scientific text",
            "d) Technical text"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Note taking is based on effective listening. While note taking, listener has to concentrate on contents of the speech."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a deterrent to the listening process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lack of interest",
            "b) Ego",
            "c) Confidence",
            "d) Fear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At the time of noting, the listener should try to understand the speech instead of evaluating. Also don’t try to anticipate what the speaker will say."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a barrier to listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical barrier",
            "b) Cultural barrier",
            "c) Linguistic barrier",
            "d) Written barrier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are six barriers to listening. They are: physical, physiological, linguistic, cultural barriers, speech decoding and oral discourse analysis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Which is the main barrier to listening?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical barrier",
            "b) Linguistic barrier",
            "c) Cultural barrier",
            "d) Physiological barrier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Physical barrier is the main barrier to listening. These are caused by noise, physical distractions. Noise is the biggest physical hurdle in listening. "
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a physiological barrier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fear",
            "b) Different perception",
            "c) Gel effect",
            "d) Halo effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are nine physiological barriers. They are: fear, different perception, misunderstanding, halo effect, inattentiveness, emotions, abstracting, drawing hasty conclusions and polarisation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Which of these is based on faith?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fear",
            "b) Halo effect",
            "c) Emotions",
            "d) Different perception"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Halo effect is based on faith, i.e., trust or distrust of the listener on the speaker. If the listener feels the speaker tells truth whatever he says is correct. "
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "When people take extreme positions what is it called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fear",
            "b) Halo effect",
            "c) Emotions",
            "d) Polarisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Some people take extreme position or stand on some issues and do not want to compromise or understand the other side. This is called polarization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Which of these occur because of difference in language?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical barriers",
            "b) Linguistic barriers",
            "c) Cultural barriers",
            "d) Speech decoding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Linguistic barriers occur when the people speak different languages. They have different mother tongues. This creates problems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Barriers which are caused because of different meanings of a word to different people is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) different perception",
            "b) semantic distortions",
            "c) physical barriers",
            "d) cultural barriers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Semantic distortions is one of the barriers in listening. The words often means different things to different people which is a distortion of non deliberate nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Which of these barriers occur when people belong to different religious backgrounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical barriers",
            "b) Linguistic barriers",
            "c) Cultural barriers",
            "d) Speech decoding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cultural barriers occur when the speaker and listener are from different cultural background or religious background."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Who among these bow down to greet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Japanese",
            "b) Americans",
            "c) Indians",
            "d) French"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Japanese bow down to greet, Westerners and Americans have gentle kiss on the cheeks of each other. One should avoid offending the people from other cultures."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a step in speech decoding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Listening",
            "b) Writing",
            "c) Translating",
            "d) Understanding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three steps in speech decoding. They are: listening of speech, translation and understanding by the listener. "
    }
]